<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-US"><title type="text">雪岛不白</title><subtitle type="html">Blog of bubai in English.</subtitle><updated>2023-04-24T15:10:22+08:00</updated><id>https://bubais.top/en/</id><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://bubais.top/en/"/><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://bubais.top/en/atom.xml"/><author><name>不白</name><uri>https://bubais.top/en/</uri><email>nowhitestar@gmail.com</email></author><rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><generator uri="https://gohugo.io/" version="0.111.3">Hugo</generator><entry><title type="text">Hybrid architectures for Web3 data infrastructures, an exploration based on the a16z article</title><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://bubais.top/en/tech/web3-data-infra/"/><id>https://bubais.top/en/tech/web3-data-infra/</id><updated>2023-04-24T15:10:21+08:00</updated><published>2023-04-06T10:50:02+08:00</published><author><name>不白</name><uri>https://bubais.top/</uri><email>nowhitestar@gmail.com</email></author><rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">The popularity of Chat GPT and GPT-4 has shown us the power of artificial intelligence. Behind artificial intelligence, in addition to algorithms, what is more, important is massive data. Around the data, we have built a large-scale complex system, the value of which mainly comes from business intelligence (Business Intelligence, BI) and artificial intelligence (Artificial Intelligence, AI).</summary><content type="html">&lt;p>The popularity of Chat GPT and GPT-4 has shown us the power of artificial intelligence. Behind artificial intelligence, in addition to algorithms, what is more, important is massive data. Around the data, we have built a large-scale complex system, the value of which mainly comes from business intelligence (Business Intelligence, BI) and artificial intelligence (Artificial Intelligence, AI). Due to the rapid growth of data volumes in the Internet age, data infrastructure work, and best practices are also evolving rapidly. In the past two years, the core system of the data infrastructure technology stack has been very stable, and the supporting tools and applications are also growing rapidly.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="web2-data-infrastructure-architecture">Web2 Data Infrastructure Architecture&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Cloud data warehouses (e.g., Snowflake, etc.) are growing rapidly, primarily focusing on SQL user and business intelligence user scenarios. Adoption of other technologies is also accelerating, with data lakes (e.g., Databricks) experiencing unprecedented customer growth, and heterogeneity in the data technology stack will coexist.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Other core data systems, such as data acquisition and transformation, have proven equally durable. This is particularly evident in the modern data intelligence space, where combinations of Fivetran and dbt (or similar technologies) can be found almost everywhere. The combination of Databricks/Spark, Confluent/Kafka, and Astronomer/Airflow is also becoming the de facto standard.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://s2.loli.net/2023/04/06/PYoSezxOZdJK8cs.png" alt="Source: a16z" title="Source: a16z">&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Data Sources&lt;/strong> end generates relevant business and operational data;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Data Extraction and Transformation&lt;/strong> responsible for extracting data from business systems (E), transferring to storage, aligning formats between data sources and destinations (L) and sending analyzed data back to business systems as required;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Data storage&lt;/strong> storing data in a format that can be queried and processed, requiring optimization toward low cost, high scalability and analytical effort;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Querying and processing&lt;/strong> translates high-level programming languages (typically in SQL, Python, or Java/Scala) into low-end data processing tasks. Executing queries and data models based on stored data using distributed computing, including historical analysis (describing past occurrences) and predictive analysis (describing future expected events);&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Transformation&lt;/strong> Converting data into analytically usable structures, managing processes and resources;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Analysis and Output&lt;/strong> is an interface for analysts and data scientists to provide traceable insight and collaboration, present the results of data analysis to internal and external users, and embed data models into user-facing applications.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>With the rapid development of the data ecosystem, the concept of &amp;quot;data platforms&amp;quot; has emerged. From an industry perspective, the defining characteristic of a platform is the technical and economic interdependence of an influential platform provider and many third-party developers. From a platform perspective, the data technology stack is divided into a &amp;quot;front-end&amp;quot; and a &amp;quot;back-end.&amp;quot;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>&amp;quot;Back-end&amp;quot; roughly includes data extraction, storage, processing, and transformation&lt;/strong>, and has begun to consolidate around several cloud service providers. As a result, customer data is collected in a standard system, and vendors are investing heavily in making this data easily accessible to other developers. This is also a fundamental design principle of systems like Databricks and is implemented through systems like the SQL standard and custom compute APIs like Snowflake.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;quot;Front-end&amp;quot; engineers leverage this single integration point to build various new applications. **They rely on data that has been cleaned and integrated into a data warehouse/lake warehouse without worrying about how they were generated. A single customer can build and buy many applications on top of one core data system. ** We are even starting to see traditional enterprise systems, such as financial or product analytics, being refactored using warehouse-native architectures.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As the data technology stack gradually matures, the data applications on the data platform also surge. Due to standardization, adopting new data platforms has never been more important, and correspondingly maintaining platforms has become extremely important. At scale, platforms can be very valuable. There is intense competition among core data system vendors for current budgets and long-term platform positions. &lt;strong>The astonishing valuations of data ingestion and transformation companies are easier to understand if you consider that data ingestion and transformation modules are a core part of emerging data platforms.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, these technology stacks have been shaped by a data utilization approach dominated by large companies. As society's understanding of data deepens, it is believed that data, like land, labor, capital, and technology, &lt;a href="http://www.gov.cn/zhengce/2020-04/09/content_5500622.htm">are all marketable factors of production&lt;/a>. As one of the five factors of production, it is the asset value of data reflected behind it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The current technology stack is inadequate to enable the allocation of data element markets. New data infrastructures are developing and evolving in Web3, which is closely integrated with blockchain technology. These infrastructures will be embedded in modern data infrastructure architectures to enable &lt;strong>data ownership rights definition, circulation transactions, revenue distribution, and factor governance&lt;/strong>. These four areas are critical from &lt;a href="http://www.gov.cn/zhengce/2022-12/19/content_5732695.htm">a government regulatory perspective&lt;/a> and require special attention.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="web3-hybrid-data-infrastructure-architecture">Web3 Hybrid Data Infrastructure Architecture&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Inspired by the a16z &lt;a href="https://a16z.com/2020/10/15/emerging-architectures-for-modern-data-infrastructure/">Unified Data Infrastructure Architecture (2.0)&lt;/a> and incorporating our understanding of the Web3 infrastructure architecture, we propose the following Web3 Hybrid Data Infrastructure Architecture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://s2.loli.net/2023/04/06/XlVc8P5u9IDCpx4.jpg" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Orange is the technology stack unit that is unique to Web3. Since decentralization is still in its early stages of development, most applications in the Web3 space are still using this hybrid data infrastructure architecture. The vast majority of applications are not true &amp;quot;&lt;a href="https://jacob.energy/hyperstructures.html">superstructures&lt;/a>&amp;quot;. Hyperarchitecture is a non-stoppable, free, valuable, scalable, license-free, positive externality, and trustworthy neutrality. It exists as a public good for the digital world, public infrastructure for the &amp;quot;metaverse&amp;quot; world. This requires a completely decentralized underlying architecture to support it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The traditional data infrastructure architecture evolved in response to the business development of the enterprise. a16z summarizes it in two systems (analytics and business systems) and three scenarios (modern business intelligence, multi-model data processing, artificial intelligence, and machine learning). This is a summary made from the perspective of the business - data for the growth of the business.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://s2.loli.net/2023/03/21/sLOo37SQNXn5RDV.png" alt="Source: a16z" title="Source: a16z">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, not only enterprises, society, and individuals should benefit from the productivity improvement from the data element. Countries worldwide have introduced policies and regulations one after another, hoping to regulate the use of data from the regulatory level and promote the circulation of data. This includes various data banks that are common in Japan, data exchanges that have recently emerged in China, and trading platforms that have been widely used in Europe and the United States, such as BDEX (USA), Streamr (Switzerland), DAWEX (France) and CARUSO, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As data begins to be titled, traded in flow, distributed, and governed, their systems and scenarios go beyond empowering companies to make decisions and grow their businesses themselves. These systems and scenarios either need to leverage blockchain technology or strongly rely on policy regulation. web3 is a natural ground for data factor markets, which technically eliminates the possibility of cheating and can greatly reduce regulatory pressure, allowing data to existing as a true factor of production and be allocated in a market-based manner.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://s2.loli.net/2023/04/06/d4aSnCHtY6GyDeU.jpg" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the Web3 context, the new paradigm of data utilization includes market systems that host mobile data elements and public systems that manage public data elements. They cover three new data business scenarios: property data development integration, composable initial data layers, and public data mining.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Some of these scenarios are tightly integrated with traditional data infrastructures and belong to Web3 hybrid data infrastructure architectures. In contrast, others are detached from traditional architectures and are fully supported by new technologies native to Web3.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="web3-and-the-data-economy">Web3 and the Data Economy&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The data economy marketplace is the key to allocating data elements, including developing and integrating product data and the initial data layer market with composability. In an efficient and compliant data economy market, &lt;a href="http://www.gov.cn/zhengce/2022-12/19/content_5732695.htm">the following points are important&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>data ownership rights&lt;/strong> are key to securing rights and compliant use and should be disposed of in a structured allocation, while data use requires confirmation of authorization mechanisms. Each participant should have the relevant rights and interests.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Circulation transactions&lt;/strong> must be combined on and off-site as well as compliant and efficient. It should be based on four principles: data source can be confirmed, use scope can be defined, circulation process can be traced, and security risk can be prevented.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Revenue distribution&lt;/strong> system needs to be efficient and fair. According to the principle of &amp;quot;who inputs, who contributes, who benefits&amp;quot;, the government can guide and regulate the distribution of data elements.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Factor governance&lt;/strong> is secure, controllable, flexible, and inclusive. This requires an innovative government data governance mechanism, the establishment of a data elements market credit system, and encourage enterprises to actively participate in the construction of a data elements market around data sources, data ownership rights, data quality, data use, etc., the implementation of the data circulation transaction statement and commitment system for data vendors and third-party professional service organizations.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The above principles are the basic principles for regulators to consider the data economy. These principles can be used to think about three scenarios: property data development and integration, composable initial data layers, and public data mining. What kind of infrastructure do we need to support this? What kind of value can these infrastructures capture at what stages?&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="scenario-1--data-ownership--rights-development-and-integration">Scenario 1: Data ownership rights development and integration&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://s2.loli.net/2023/04/06/trBdNm1Z8T9Uw6k.jpg" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the process of property rights data development, it is necessary to establish a &lt;strong>categorical and hierarchical rights confirmation and authorization mechanism&lt;/strong> to determine the ownership, use rights, and management rights of public, corporate, and personal data. According to the data source and generation characteristics, the property rights of data are defined through &amp;quot;data adaptation&amp;quot;. Among them, typical projects include Navigate, Streamr Network, KYVE, etc. These projects realize data quality standardization, data collection, and interface standardization through technical means, confirm the rights of off-chain data in some form, and carry out data classification and hierarchical authorization through smart contracts or internal logic systems.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The applicable data types in this scenario are non-public data, namely enterprise and personal data. The value of data elements should be activated by &amp;quot;common use and shared benefits&amp;quot; in a market-oriented manner.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Enterprise data includes all kinds of market subjects in the production and business activities collected and processed data that do not involve personal information and public interests. Market subjects enjoy the rights and interests to hold, use and obtain benefits in accordance with the law, as well as the right to receive reasonable returns for their input labor and other factor contributions.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Personal data requires data processors to collect, hold, host, and use data per the scope of individual authorization and the law. Use innovative technical means to promote the anonymization of personal information and to safeguard the security of information and personal privacy when using personal information data. Explore mechanisms for trustees to represent the interests of individuals and supervise the collection, processing, and use of personal information data by market entities. For special personal information data related to national security, the use of relevant units may be authorized in accordance with the law and regulations.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="scenario-2-combinable-initial-data-layers">Scenario 2: Combinable initial data layers&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://s2.loli.net/2023/04/06/K8rnL5ZEhyPuDRV.jpg" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Composable initial data layers are an important part of the data economy market. Unlike general property rights data, the most obvious feature of this part of data is that the standard data format needs to be defined through &amp;quot;data schema management&amp;quot;. Different from the quality, collection, and interface standardization of &amp;quot;data adaptation&amp;quot;, the emphasis here is on the standardization of data models, including standard data formats and standard data models. Ceramic and Lens are the pioneers in this field. They respectively guarantee the standard mode of off-chain (decentralized storage) and on-chain data, thus making data composable.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Built on top of these data schema management tools are composable initial data layers, often called &amp;quot;data layers&amp;quot;, such as Cyberconnect, KNN3, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The combinable initial data layers are less involved in the Web2 technology stack, but ceramic-based hot data reading tools break this point, which will be a critical breakthrough. Many similar data do not need to be stored on the blockchain, and storing them on the blockchain is difficult. Still, they need to be stored on a decentralized network, such as high-frequency low-value density such as user posts, likes, and comments Data, and Ceramic provides a storage paradigm for this type of data.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Composable initial data is a key scenario for innovation in the new era, and it is also an important symbol of the end of data hegemony and monopoly. It &lt;a href="https://a16z.com/2019/05/09/data-network-effects-moats/">can solve&lt;/a> the cold start problem of start-ups in terms of data, combining mature data sets and new data sets so that Startups can build a data competitive advantage faster. At the same time, it lets start-ups focus on incremental data value and freshness to win continuous competitiveness for their innovative ideas. This way, large data will not become a moat for large companies.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="scenario-3-public-data-mining">Scenario 3: Public Data Mining&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://s2.loli.net/2023/04/06/ExU31nwQdTjk57h.jpg" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Common data mining is not a new use case but has received unprecedented prominence in the Web3 technology stack.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Traditional public data includes public data generated by party and government agencies, enterprises, and institutions performing their duties according to law or providing public services. Regulatory agencies encourage providing such data to society in the form of models, verification, and other products and services per the requirements of &amp;quot;original data not out of domain, data usable but not visible&amp;quot; on the premise of protecting personal privacy and ensuring public safety. They use traditional technology stacks (blue and some orange, orange represents the intersection of multiple types of technology stacks, the same as below).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In Web3, the transaction data and activity data on the blockchain are another type of public data, which is characterized by &amp;quot;available and visible&amp;quot;, so it lacks data privacy, data security, and data use confirmation authorization capabilities, which is a real &amp;quot; Public goods&amp;quot; (Public Goods). They use a technology stack (yellow and partially orange) with blockchain and smart contracts at its core.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The data on decentralized storage is mostly Web3 application data other than transactions. At present, it is mainly file and object storage, and the corresponding technology stack is still immature (green and some orange). The production and mining of this type of public data utilize storage common issues, including hot and cold storage, indexing, state synchronization, rights management, computation, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Many data applications have emerged in this scenario. They are not data infrastructure but more data tools, including Nansen, Dune, NFT Scan, 0x Scope, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="case-data-exchange">Case: Data Exchange&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Data exchange is a platform where data is traded as a commodity. They can be categorized and compared based on transaction objects, pricing mechanisms, quality assurance, etc. Data Stream X, Dawex, and Ocean Protocol are typical market data exchanges.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ocean Protocol (200 million market cap) is an open-source protocol that enables businesses and individuals to exchange and liquidate data and data-based services. The protocol is based on the Ethereum blockchain and uses &amp;quot;datatokens&amp;quot; to control access to datasets. A data token is a special ERC20 token representing ownership or access to a dataset or a data service. Users can purchase or earn data tokens to access the information they need.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The technical architecture of Ocean Protocol consists of the following main components:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Providers: Providers providing data or data services can earn revenue by issuing and selling their own data passes through Ocean Protocol.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Consumers: Demanders who buy and use data or data services can purchase or earn the data passes they need to gain access through Ocean Protocol.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Marketplaces: An open, transparent, and fair marketplace for data transactions provided by Ocean Protocol or a third party that connects providers and consumers globally and offers data passes in multiple types and domains. Marketplaces can help organizations discover new business opportunities, increase revenue streams, optimize operational efficiency, and create value.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Network: refers to a decentralized network layer provided by Ocean Protocol that supports data exchange of different types and sizes and ensures security, trust, and transparency in the data transaction process. The network layer is a set of smart contracts that are used to register data, record ownership information, facilitate secure data exchange, etc.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Curator (Curator): refers to a role in an ecosystem responsible for screening, managing, and reviewing datasets. They are responsible for reviewing information about the dataset's source, content, format, and license to ensure that the dataset meets standards and can be trusted and used by other users.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Verifier: A role in an ecosystem that verifies, vets data transactions and data services, and reviews and validates transactions between data service providers and consumers to ensure the quality, availability, and accuracy of data services.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://s2.loli.net/2022/09/08/NabTRcsoxiSmylW.png" alt="Source: Ocean Protocol" title="Source: Ocean Protocol">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;quot;Data services&amp;quot; data providers create include data, algorithms, computation, storage, analysis, and curation. These components are tied to the service's execution agreements (service-level agreements), secure computing, access control, and permissions. Essentially, this controls access to a &amp;quot;cloud service suite&amp;quot; through smart contracts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://s2.loli.net/2022/09/08/9AO7PqCBrTIv4tn.png" alt="Source: Ocean Protocol" title="Source: Ocean Protocol">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The advantage is that,&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Open-source, flexible, and extensible protocols help organizations and individuals create unique data ecosystems.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The decentralized network layer based on blockchain technology can ensure the security, credibility, and transparency of the data transaction process while protecting providers' and consumers' privacy and rights.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>An open, transparent, and fair data market that can connect providers and consumers worldwide and provide data certificates of various types and fields.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Ocean Protocol is a typical representative of hybrid architecture. Its data can be stored in different places, including traditional cloud storage services, decentralized storage networks, or the data provider's own servers. The protocol uses data tokens (datatokens) and non-homogeneous tokens (data NFTs) to identify and manage data ownership and access rights. In addition, the protocol also provides the function of computing to data (compute-to-data), enabling data consumers to analyze and process data without exposing the original data.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://s2.loli.net/2023/03/22/nkgzXBirsUDYtP7.png" alt="Source: Ocean Protocol" title="Source: Ocean Protocol">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Although Ocean Protocol is one of the complete data trading platforms on the market at this stage, it still faces many challenges:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Establish an effective trust mechanism to increase the trust between data providers and demanders and reduce transaction risks. For example, establish a data element market credit system, and carry out certification and verification through the blockchain to identify untrustworthy behaviors in data transactions, incentives for keeping promises, punishment for untrustworthiness, credit restoration, objection handling, etc.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Establish a reasonable pricing mechanism to reflect the true value of data products, incentivize data providers to provide high-quality data, and attract more demanders.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Establish a unified standard specification to facilitate interoperability and compatibility between data of different formats, types, sources, and purposes.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="case-data-model-marketplace">Case: Data Model Marketplace&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Ceramic mentions in their &lt;a href="https://blog.ceramic.network/into-the-dataverse/">Data Universe&lt;/a> the open data model marketplace they want to create because data needs interoperability and it can contribute significantly to productivity gains. Such a data model marketplace is achieved through an urgent consensus on the data model, similar to the ERC contract standard in Ether, from which developers can choose a functional template to have an application that conforms to all the data in that data model. At this stage, such a marketplace is not a trading marketplace.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Regarding the data model, a simple example is that in a decentralized social network, the data model can be reduced to 4 parameters, which are&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;code>PostList&lt;/code>: stores the index of user posts&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;code>Post&lt;/code>: stores individual posts&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;code>Profile&lt;/code>: stores the user's profile&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;code>FollowList&lt;/code>: stores the user's follow list&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>So how can data models be created, shared, and reused on Ceramic to enable cross-application data interoperability?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ceramic provides a Data Models Registry (&lt;a href="https://github.com/ceramicstudio/datamodels">Data Models Registry&lt;/a>), an open source, community-built, reusable application data model for the Ceramic repository. Here, developers can openly register, discover, and reuse existing data models—the foundation for customer operations applications built on shared data models. Currently, it is based on Github storage, and in the future, it will be decentralized on Ceramic.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All data models added to the registry are automatically published under the &lt;code>npm&lt;/code> package of &lt;strong>@datamodels&lt;/strong>. Any developer can install one or more data models using &lt;code>@datamodels/model - name&lt;/code>. These models are available for storing or retrieving data at runtime using any IDX client, including DID Data Store or Self.ID.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In addition, Ceramic has built a &lt;a href="https://github.com/ceramicstudio/datamodels/discussions">Data Models forum&lt;/a> based on GitHub. Each model in the data model registry has its own discussion thread on this forum. The community can comment and discuss it. At the same time, it is also a place for developers to publish their ideas on data models so as to obtain the opinions of the community before adding them to the registry. At present, everything is in the early stage. There are not many data models in the registry. The data models included in the registry should be evaluated by the community and called the CIP standard, just like the smart contract standard of Ethereum, which provides data composability.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="case-decentralized-data-warehouse">Case: Decentralized Data Warehouse&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.spaceandtime.io/">Space and Time&lt;/a> is the first decentralized data warehouse to connect on-chain and off-chain data to support a new generation of smart contract use cases. Space and Time (SxT) has the industry's most mature blockchain indexing service. The SxT data warehouse also employs new cryptography called The SxT data warehouse also employs new cryptography called Proof of SQL™ to generate verifiable, tamper-proof results, allowing developers to join untrusted on-chain and off-chain-data-in a simple SQL format and load the results directly into smart contracts, supporting sub-second queries and enterprise-level analytics in a fully tamper-proof and blockchain-anchored manner.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://s2.loli.net/2023/04/06/ncl7ksFVjiKxGUJ.png" alt="Source: Space and Time" title="Source: Space and Time">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Space and Time is a two-tier network with a validator layer and a data warehouse. the success of the SxT platform depends on the seamless interaction of the validator and the data warehouse to facilitate simple and secure querying of both on-chain and off-chain data.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A data warehouse consists of database networks and computes clusters controlled by and routed to them by space and time validators. Space and time adopt a flexible storage solution: HTAP (Hybrid transactional/analytic processing).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The validator monitors, commands, and validates the services provided by these clusters, then orchestrates the data flow and queries between end users and data warehouse clusters. Validators provide a means for data to enter a system (such as a blockchain index) and data to exit a system (such as a smart contract).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Routing - supports transactional and query interactions with a network of decentralized data warehouses&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Streaming - acts as a sink for high-volume customer streaming (event-driven) workloads&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Consensus - Provides high-performance Byzantine Fault Tolerance for data entering and exiting the platform&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Query Proof - provide SQL proof to the platform&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Table Anchor - provide proof of storage to the platform by anchoring the table on the chain&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Oracle - supports Web3 interactions, including smart contract event listening and cross-chain messaging/relaying&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Security - preventing unauthenticated and unauthorized access to the platform&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://s2.loli.net/2023/04/06/G4C7IYwge89JMtr.png" alt="Source: Space and Time" title="Source: Space and Time">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Space and Time as a platform is the world's first decentralized data structure, opening up a powerful but underserved market: data sharing. Within the Space and Time platform, companies can share data freely and use smart contracts to trade the shared data. &lt;a href="https://docs.spaceandtime.io/docs/proof-of-sql">Additionally, datasets can be proof-of-sql&lt;/a> monetized and aggregated without giving consumers access to the raw data. Data consumers can trust that aggregations are accurate without seeing the data itself, so data providers no longer have to be data consumers. It is for this reason that the combination of SQL proofs and data structure schemas has the potential to democratize data manipulation, as anyone can contribute to ingesting, transforming, and serving datasets.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="web3-data-governance-and-discovery">Web3 Data Governance and Discovery&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Currently, the Web3 data infrastructure lacks a practical and efficient data governance architecture. However, a practical and efficient data governance infrastructure is essential to configure the data elements of each participant's relevant rights and interests.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>For the data source, it is necessary to have informed consent and the right to acquire, copy and transfer the data itself freely.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For data processors, they need to have the right to self-control, use data and obtain benefits.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For data derivatives, operating rights are required.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Currently, Web3 data governance capabilities are single, assets and data (including ceramics) can only be controlled by controlling private keys, and almost no hierarchical classification configuration capability exists. Recently, the innovative mechanisms of Tableland, FEVM, and Greenfield can achieve trustless data governance to a certain extent. Traditional data governance tools such as Collibra can only be used within the enterprise and only have platform-level trust. At the same time, non-decentralized technology also makes it impossible to prevent personal evil and single points of failure. Through data governance tools such as Tableland, the security technologies, standards, and solutions required for the data circulation process can be guaranteed.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="case-tableland">Case: Tableland&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Tableland Network is a decentralized web3 protocol for structured relational data, starting with Ethereum (EVM) and EVM-compatible L2. With Tableland, it is now possible to implement traditional web2 relational database functionality by leveraging the blockchain layer for access control. However, Tableland is not a new database &lt;strong>- just web3 native relational tables&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tableland offers a new way to enable dapps to store relational data in web3-native networks without these tradeoffs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Solutions&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://s2.loli.net/2023/04/06/hP4jKEHgT3eiInM.png" alt="Source: Tableland" title="Source: Tableland">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With Tableland, metadata can be mutated (with access controls if needed), queried (using familiar SQL), and composable (with other tables on Tableland) - all in a fully decentralized manner.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://s2.loli.net/2023/04/06/ndTLSx8U6PhrJNj.png" alt="Source: Tableland" title="Source: Tableland">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tableland breaks down a traditional relational database into two main components: an on-chain registry with access control logic (ACL) and an off-chain (decentralized) table. Every table in Tableland is initially minted as an ERC721 token on a base EVM compatibility layer. Thus, on-chain table owners can set ACL permissions on the table, while off-chain, the Tableland network manages the creation and subsequent alteration of the table itself. Linking between on-chain and off-chain is handled at the contract level. It points to the Tableland network (using base URI + token URI, much like many existing ERC721 tokens that use IPFS gateways or escrow servers for metadata).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://s2.loli.net/2023/04/06/B8Fkul6f1gsrwyo.png" alt="Source: Tableland" title="Source: Tableland">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Only people with the appropriate on-chain privileges can write to a particular table. However, table reads do not have to be on-chain operations and can use the Tableland gateway; therefore, read queries are free and can come from simple front-end requests or other non-EVM blockchains. To use Tableland, a table must first be created (i.e., cast on the chain as ERC721). The deployment address is initially set to the table owner, and this owner can set permissions for any other users who try to interact with the table to make changes. For example, the owner can set rules for who can update/insert/delete values, what data they can change, and even decide if they want to transfer ownership of the other side of the table. In addition, more complex queries can join data from multiple tables (owned or unowned) to create a fully dynamic and composable relational data layer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Consider the following diagram, which summarizes a new user's interaction with a table that has been deployed to Tableland by some dapp:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://s2.loli.net/2023/04/06/8FHr6b1wL3f7ejJ.png" alt="Source: Tableland" title="Source: Tableland">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here is the overall flow of information:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>A new user interacts with the dapp's UI and tries to update some information stored in a Tableland table.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The dapp calls the Tableland registration smart contract to run this SQL statement, and this contract checks the dapp's smart contract, which contains a custom ACL that defines the permissions of this new user. There are a few points to note:
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Custom ACLs in separate smart contracts for dapps are a completely optional but advanced use case; developers don't need to implement custom ACLs and can use the default policy of the Tableland Registry smart contract (only the owner has full permissions).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You can also use &lt;a href="https://docs.tableland.xyz/faqs#4dcbf05f97a74829a0ba6d5bb6ed1a76">Gateway&lt;/a> to write queries instead of calling Tableland smart contracts directly. There will always be an option for dapps to call Tableland smart contracts directly, but any query can be sent through the &lt;a href="https://docs.tableland.xyz/faqs#4dcbf05f97a74829a0ba6d5bb6ed1a76">Gateway&lt;/a>, which will relay the query to the smart contract on a subsidized basis.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Tableland smart contract takes the user's SQL statements and permissions, incorporating these into emitted events that describe the SQL-based actions to be taken.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Tableland Validator node listens to these events and then takes one of the following actions:
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>If the user has the correct permissions to write to the table, the validator will run SQL commands accordingly (insert a new row into the table or update an existing value) and broadcast the confirmation data to the Tableland network.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If the user does not have the correct permissions, the Validator will not perform any operations on the table.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If the request is a simple read query, the corresponding data is returned; Tableland is a completely open relational data network where anyone can perform read-only queries on any table.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Dapps can reflect any updates on the Tableland network via the &lt;a href="https://docs.tableland.xyz/faqs#4dcbf05f97a74829a0ba6d5bb6ed1a76">Gateway&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>(Usage scenario) What to avoid&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Personally identifiable data -&lt;/strong> Tableland is an open network; anyone can read data from any table. Therefore, personal data should not be stored in Tableland.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>High-frequency, sub-second writes&lt;/strong> - e.g., high-frequency trading robots.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Storing every user interaction in the application&lt;/strong> - keeping this data in Web3 tables, such as keystrokes or clicks, may not make sense. The frequency of writes can lead to high costs.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Very large data sets&lt;/strong> - These should be avoided and are best handled through file storage, using solutions such as IPFS, Filecoin, or Arweave. However, pointers to these locations and associated metadata are actually a good use case for Tableland tables.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h1 id="thoughts-on-valuation-capture">Thoughts on valuation capture&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The different units have an irreplaceable role in the overall data infrastructure architecture, and the value of their value capture is mainly reflected in the market value/valuation and estimated earnings, which can be obtained from the following conclusions:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Data Source&lt;/strong> is the module with the largest value capture &lt;strong>in the whole architecture&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Data Replication, Transformation, Streaming, and Data Warehousing&lt;/strong> are the next most important&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Analytics layer&lt;/strong> may have good cash flow, but there will be an upper limit to valuation&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Companies/projects on the left of the structure chart tend to capture greater value.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="industry-concentration">Industry Concentration&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>According to incomplete statistical analysis from the companies in the graph above, industry concentration is judged as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>the highest industry concentration is &lt;strong>data storage&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>data query and processing&lt;/strong> two modules&lt;/li>
&lt;li>the industry concentration is medium is data extraction and conversion&lt;/li>
&lt;li>the two modules with low industry concentration are data source, analysis, and output&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The industry concentration of data sources, analysis, and output is low. The preliminary judgment is that different business scenarios lead to the emergence of vertical scenario leaders in each business scenario, such as Oracle in the database, Stripe in third-party services, Salesforce in enterprise services, Tableau in dashboard analysis, Sisense in embedded analysis, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The reason for the moderate industry concentration of data extraction and conversion modules is initially judged to be due to the technology-oriented nature of the business attributes. The modular form of middleware also makes the switching cost relatively low.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The data storage and query and processing modules with the highest industry concentration are initially judged to be due to the single business scenario, high technical content, high start-up cost, and high cost of subsequent switching, which gives the company/project a strong first-mover advantage and network effect.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="thoughts-on-business-models-and-exit-paths-for-data-protocols">Thoughts on business models and exit paths for data protocols&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Judging from the time of establishment and listing,&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Most companies/projects established before 2010 are data source companies/projects. The mobile Internet has not yet emerged, and the data is not very large. There are also some data storage and analysis output projects, mainly dashboards.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>From 2010 to 2014, on the eve of the rise of the mobile Internet, data storage and query projects such as Snowflake and Databricks were born, data extraction and conversion projects also began to appear, and a set of mature big data management technology solutions gradually improved. There are a large number of analysis output projects, mainly dashboards.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>From 2015 to 2020, query and processing projects have sprung up, and many data extraction and conversion projects are also emerging so that people can better exert the power of big data.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>From 2020 onwards, newer real-time analytics databases and data lake solutions emerged, such as Clickhouse and Tabular.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Infrastructure improvement is the premise of the so-called &amp;quot;mass adoption&amp;quot;. During the period of large-scale application, there are still new opportunities. Still, these opportunities are almost only &amp;quot;middleware&amp;quot;, and the underlying data warehouse, data source, and other solutions are almost a winner-takes-all situation unless there is a technically substantial Sexual breakthrough. Otherwise, it will be difficult to grow up.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And analysis output projects are opportunities for entrepreneurial projects no matter what period they are in. But it is also constantly iteratively innovating and doing new things based on new scenarios. Tableau, which appeared before 2010, occupied most of the desktop dashboard analysis tools. New scenarios emerged later, such as more professional-oriented DS/ML tools, A more comprehensive data workstation, and a more SaaS-oriented embedded analysis.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Looking at the current data protocol of Web3 from this perspective:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The data source and storage projects are not yet determined, but the leaders are emerging. The state storage on the chain is led by Ethereum (220 billion market value), while the decentralized storage is led by Filecoin (2.3 billion market value) and Arweave (280 million market value). There may be a sudden emergence of Greenfield. ——Highest value capture&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There is still room for innovation in data extraction and conversion projects. The data oracle machine Chainlink (market value of 3.8 billion) is just the beginning. Event streaming and stream processing infrastructure Ceramic and more projects will appear, but there is not much space. - Moderate value capture&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For query and processing projects, the Graph (with a market value of 1.2 billion) has been able to meet most of the needs, and the type and quantity of projects have not yet reached the explosive period. - Moderate value capture&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Data analysis projects, mainly Nansen and Dune (valued at 1 billion), need new scenarios for new opportunities. NFT Scan and NFT Go are similar to new scenarios, but they are only content updates, not analysis logic New requirements at the /paradigm level. — Moderate value capture, strong cash flow.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>But Web3 is not a copy of Web2 nor a complete evolution of Web2. Web3 has very original missions and scenarios, thus giving birth to business scenarios that are completely different from before (the first three scenarios are all abstractions that can be made now).&lt;/p></content></entry><entry><title type="text">When we talk about Web3 data, what are we talking about?</title><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://bubais.top/en/tech/web3-data/"/><id>https://bubais.top/en/tech/web3-data/</id><updated>2023-04-24T15:10:21+08:00</updated><published>2022-09-27T10:50:02+08:00</published><author><name>不白</name><uri>https://bubais.top/</uri><email>nowhitestar@gmail.com</email></author><rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">To figure out what we're talking about when we're talking about Web3 data, we first need to figure out what data looks like in Web2. We will discuss it from the full life cycle of data generation, collection, storage, management and use. Before that, let's first figure out how data is defined.</summary><content type="html">&lt;p>To figure out what we're talking about when we're talking about Web3 data, we first need to figure out what data looks like in Web2. We will discuss it from the full life cycle of data generation, collection, storage, management and use. Before that, let's first figure out how data is defined.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Data is classified into personal information, public data and legal person data in the &amp;quot;Guidelines for the Practice of Cyber ​​Security Standards - Guidelines for Data Classification and Classification&amp;quot; (Draft for Comments-v1.0-202109) issued by the National Information Security Standardization Technical Committee of China. The specific definitions and examples are as follows.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th style="text-align:left">Data Classification&lt;/th>
&lt;th style="text-align:left">Category Definition&lt;/th>
&lt;th style="text-align:left">Example&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Public data&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Data collected and generated by public management and service agencies in the process of performing public management and service duties in accordance with the law, and data collected and generated by other organizations and individuals in the provision of public services that involve public interests&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Such as government affairs data, and Provide data related to public interests in public services such as water supply, power supply, gas supply, heating supply, public transportation, elderly care, education, medical care, postal services, etc.&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Personal information&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Various information recorded electronically or otherwise relating to an identified or identifiable natural person, excluding anonymized information&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">such as personally identifiable information, personal biometric information, personal property information, personal communications information, personal location information, personal health and physiological information, etc.&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Legal Person Data&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Data collected and generated by an organization in the process of production, operation and internal management&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Such as business data, business management data, system operation and safety data, etc.&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Above each category, it is further divided into 5 levels according to the harm object and degree of data leakage: public level (level 1), internal level (level 2), sensitive level (level 3), important level (level 4) and Core Level (Level 5). For public-level data, it is more like a public good, non-rival and non-exclusive. This type of data is generally provided by government/public organizations for which the benefit belongs, such as weather forecasts, macroeconomic data, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="1-data-generation-collection-and-storage">1. Data generation, collection and storage&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Public data, personal data and legal entity data are mostly generated in our daily use of computer applications, among which personal data and legal entity data are most relevant to ordinary users. So how is personal data and legal entity data generated and collected? A highly abstract Internet product system architecture diagram is shown below.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://s2.loli.net/2022/08/19/JLAQjYiv8zVhtl9.png" alt="Web2 Application Architecture" title="Web2 Application Architecture">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The bottom-level database stores the data passed from the back-end and generated by the interaction between the user and the front-end. Broadly speaking, these are user data. As far as mobile applications are concerned, data can be roughly divided into the following categories:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>User information&lt;/strong>, the user-related information recorded by the user using the application service, including the user's identity information, device, network, geographic location and even the list of applications installed on the mobile device, etc. Buried to collect.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Content data&lt;/strong>, the data generated by the user using the application service, these include any non-personal information content data that the user actively interactively writes on the application, which are part of the application service and are generally collected directly by the server data sheet.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Behavior data&lt;/strong>, the data generated by the user's interaction during the use of the application, these include the user's behavioral habits during the use of the application, such as viewing time, click rate, penetration rate, sliding situation, etc., which are generally collected by buried points .&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Log data&lt;/strong>, the data generated by the application itself during the user's use of the application, these include the application's crash log, etc.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Code data&lt;/strong>, non-user interaction data includes front-end and back-end code. Like user data, these data are stored on a centralized server somewhere.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>In this category, user information belongs to personal information data, and log and code data belong to legal entity data. Among them, content data and behavior data are worth discussing. In the Web2 era, they are more divided into their own business data by centralized entities, that is, legal person data.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Is there any difference in the application of Web3? Preethi Kasireddy's &lt;a href="https://www.preethikasireddy.com/post/the-architecture-of-a-web-3-0-application?ref=tokendaily">Web3 Product Architecture&lt;/a> can help us understand.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/5ddd80927946cdaa0e71d607/614bb2efff06e818e12a57f2_Screen%20Shot%202021-09-22%20at%206.49.04%20PM.png" alt="Web3 Product Architecture Source: Preethi Kasireddy" title="Web3 Product Architecture Source: Preethi Kasireddy">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Compared with Web2 applications, the user terminal and front-end are almost unchanged. The difference lies in the backend and the database. Users interact with node providers through the front end (rather than a centralized server), access contract code deployed on blockchains such as Ethereum (rather than the backend environment on the server), and interact. In this process, the above-mentioned types of data will also be generated. Due to the difference in technical architecture, the data generated by Web3 is not stored by a centralized server, and the storage methods of data generated in different ways may have similarities and differences.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All the data generated by the interaction of smart contracts are published on the blockchain and can be accessed by anyone. Therefore, it becomes a public product, including asset information, transaction data and contract codes. In theory, as long as the blockchain block space is large enough, any data can be stored on the blockchain, and even &lt;a href="https://www.metaid.io/">some projects&lt;/a> are trying to use the blockchain as a database to store data.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th style="text-align:left">Data Classification&lt;/th>
&lt;th style="text-align:left">Type Definition&lt;/th>
&lt;th style="text-align:left">Storage&lt;/th>
&lt;th style="text-align:left">Examples&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Asset Information&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Relevant data related to the native asset information of the blockchain&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">On-chain&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Such as token addresses, attributes, links and even content information&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Transaction data&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Relevant data related to blockchain native asset transactions&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">On-chain/off-chain&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Such as the address, time, amount, and interactive contract information of both parties to the token transaction&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Contract code&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Code data related to blockchain smart contract protocol&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">On-chain&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Such as ECR-20 contract standard&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>At the current stage, in addition to the above three types of data, most of the data generated by a Web3 application is still stored in a centralized server, including front-end code, user information, content data, behavior data, and log data. This is because the current storage infrastructure is not perfect, the project party is either limited by technical problems, or has adopted a centralized solution to ensure access speed. With the continuous development of infrastructure, there are many more and more powerful storage infrastructures, such as IFPS, Stroj, Filecoin and Ceramic, etc., and more and more applications have begun to deploy themselves on decentralized storage, such as Deploy the front-end website on IPFS and then access it through ENS, so as to build a decentralized website front-end, and use Arweave to perpetuate file data such as pictures corresponding to the NFT project, and so on.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In general, when building a Web3 application, developers usually have 3 options for storing application data:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>To store it on the blockchain, this option is very expensive, it will make the application as simple as possible, and the data is completely open. The advantage is that the application sovereignty is most directly protected.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Store the smart contract logic on the blockchain, and the rest on the traditional backend. This approach sacrifices user sovereignty and risks centralization. This is the way most Web3 apps do today.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Store the smart contract logic on the blockchain and other storages such as IPFS, Arweave, and Ceramic, and manage and update data through smart contracts. This method is expensive (Ceramic is currently free) and temporarily slow. But this approach preserves the sovereign nature of the application.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>At present, the vast majority of Web3 applications are built through the second method, and there are some specific applications that can already be built using the third method, and very few applications are built through the first method. So, which way should we choose to store it? What kind of storage method is the trend?&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="trend-decentralized-storage---data-and-application-sovereignty">Trend: Decentralized Storage - Data and Application Sovereignty&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>When it comes to 3 ways to build Web3 applications, there is one key word: sovereignty. This term is an inescapable topic when we talk about the characteristics of Web3, generally including data sovereignty and application sovereignty. So is sovereignty important? This is another topic, which is not discussed in this article. Interested can refer to related articles, such as &lt;a href="https://mirror.xyz/0x31Ae182A31Bb2c3cfd9e2E3732cc53f7606FB773/C1XwiABsyQ5-AKUCJVa4PyuEOwPe8hX-hsVXAqZfSJ4">&amp;quot;Web3 Data Market Outlook&amp;quot;&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://mirror.xyz/0xCD28A8eC501a0dDe7b27cC46965ceB7C3B35e1B7/UfvwrDOP8R6JsEotTc4n3rB8LxNa0tcLiYEx_f4C4zo">&amp;quot;Web3 - Let the &amp;quot; right to data &amp;quot;awaken&amp;quot;&lt;/a>. Here I want to cut into the only way to establish Web3 sovereignty from the perspective of data, and deduce the direction and focus of infrastructure development.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Regarding data sovereignty, it includes digital asset sovereignty and user data sovereignty. &amp;quot;&lt;a href="https://mirror.xyz/bubai.eth/SzPjJLhZeRBmwuTFKxL8MG3HcWqmLYstqSHGCuY9rc4">Vertical Liquidity: How Value Interconnects&lt;/a>&amp;quot; The article talks about how tokens can define the user's digital asset sovereignty (identity, relationship and property rights) , which is determined by a broad consensus that is hard to tamper with. Most fundamentally, the definition of these rights can be done by the blockchain itself, such as which address a token belongs to. But once it comes to the ownership of more complex digital product rights, there will be many problems, a typical one is the storage problem of pictures (or articles, etc.) corresponding to NFTs, &amp;quot;[NFT: Revolution of Digital Ownership](https:// This issue is discussed in mirror.xyz/bubai.eth/KAgr16vN8IRtjHARFQ6Wx35OmgLj9Oh2qcRkiiNw_OE)&amp;quot;. The status quo of most NFTs is that their digital counterparts are stored on a centralized server somewhere, [once the server crashes or gets hacked](&lt;a href="https://moxie.org/2022/01/07/web3-first-impressions">https://moxie.org/2022/01/07/web3-first-impressions&lt;/a> .html) , then all the user has is a string of on-chain hashes, and the real &amp;quot;item&amp;quot; behind the hash can be stolen or replaced at any time, making it worthless.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In addition, user data sovereignty, as one of the most obvious dividing lines between Web2 and Web3, is a banner for the innovation and progress of Web3. In this regard, Ceramic envisions a &lt;a href="https://blog.ceramic.network/into-the-dataverse/">data universe&lt;/a>, a composable, web-scale data ecosystem owned by everyone but not Unique to anyone. User data follows the user from one app to another, and the user acts as the hub to control their own digital universe. At present, there are almost no applications that can achieve this, Cyberconnect has made a good attempt, &lt;a href="https://mirror.xyz/cyberlab.eth/Rqr8tiXed6helt5LfSotEdLFxB6Kv_fA1Poz3K_6g0c">it creates a decentralized social graph protocol&lt;/a> Interoperability between users' social relationship data. But at present, the application does not guarantee the data sovereignty of users, although they have begun to transfer to Ceramic for construction, but everything is still on the way.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Regarding application sovereignty, some people refer to sovereign applications as &amp;quot;&lt;a href="https://jacob.energy/hyperstructures.html">hyperstructures&lt;/a>&amp;quot;, which are unstoppable, free, valuable, scalable, permissionless, positive externalities and Features such as trusted neutrality, which combine to provide a public good in the digital world, creating the infrastructure of the &amp;quot;metaverse&amp;quot; (if you believe it). At present, most of the so-called Web3 applications do not have a high degree of application sovereignty, they are not real public goods, they can be easily sanctioned and changed by power, [tornado cash incident](&lt;a href="https://home.treasury.gov/news">https://home.treasury.gov/news&lt;/a> /press-releases/jy0916) very directly illustrates the problem. One of the main reasons is that although the contract codes of these application protocol layers are published on the blockchain, components such as front-end and domain names are still controlled by third-party centralized entities.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In order to realize data sovereignty and application sovereignty, the construction method of Web3 applications is very important. The basic starting point is storage. Where does the data exist, and how can it be stored to ensure that users can have sovereignty? In general, depending on the user's data type, there can be different solutions:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Users' asset information and transaction data should be public ledger data&lt;/strong>, and it is most important to ensure verifiability on the chain, but it is very important for applications such as Aztec to appear to ensure the privacy of users' transactions on the chain. worth.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Users' user information, content data and behavioral data are regarded as personal information&lt;/strong>, and it is very important to ensure the user's right to control. With the user's consent, these data can be selectively disclosed as public goods to discover positive results. externality.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Log data and code data are used as legal person data&lt;/strong>, privatization is acceptable and necessary, but when it comes to Web3 infrastructure applications of the &amp;quot;super building&amp;quot; category, it should have the characteristics of public infrastructure. Features, the storage of application code should be open and have the ability to resist censorship beyond the platform level.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>At present, the reason why most Web3 applications adopt &amp;quot;storage of smart contract logic on the blockchain, and others on the traditional backend&amp;quot; is that there is currently no good enough decentralized infrastructure to replace the original centralized infrastructure solution.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First, decentralized storage such as IPFS, Filecoin, and Arweave are static storage, which makes them lack computing and state management capabilities, and cannot implement more advanced database-like functions (such as mutability, version control, access control, and programmable logic). ), and although Ceramic is dynamic storage, which solves these problems to a certain extent, the current access speed of Ceramic is still relatively slow, the development kit is not perfect, and its degree of decentralization has been criticized.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The main function of decentralized storage such as IPFS, Filecoin, and Arweave is to statically store unstructured data such as pictures, documents, and static codes. Because of its hard-to-tamper characteristics, it guarantees digital data such as NFT to a certain extent. Sovereignty, once the link between the on-chain hash code and the off-chain storage address is established, it is difficult to be influenced by external forces in extraordinary ways. The front-end code is built on it, which also promotes the integrity of application sovereignty. However, since the storage technology at the current stage is only storage, the lack of computing power has led to its functional support far behind the centralized server solution.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The current mainstream decentralized storage situation on the market is shown in the following table, the data is from CoinmarketCap, August 23, 2022. This table refers to &lt;a href="https://mirror.xyz/asmp.eth/LWQckvjXUxeIKH42U9c67JPYshX0XImycMl2ACz60F4">“Web3 Decentralized Storage Evolution History”&lt;/a> to summarize and update.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th style="text-align:left">Project name&lt;/th>
&lt;th style="text-align:left">Launch time&lt;/th>
&lt;th style="text-align:left">Features&lt;/th>
&lt;th style="text-align:left">Storage type&lt;/th>
&lt;th style="text-align:left">Storage fee&lt;/th>
&lt;th style="text-align:left">Security&lt;/th>
&lt;th>&lt;/th>
&lt;th>&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Storj&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">2017&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">File Storage&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Cloud Storage&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">$0.0039/GB/month&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Encryption for Privacy, File Slicing for Distributed Storage&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">STORJ&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">215&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">IPFS&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">2017&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">File Storage&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Incentive Layer/Protocol/Static Storage&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">-&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">-&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">-&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">-&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Filecoin&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">2020&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">File Storage&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Static Storage&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">$1e-7/GB/month&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Proof of Replication prevents cheating, Proof of Spacetime prevents data deletion&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">FIL&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">1678&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Arweave&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">2020&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">File Storage&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Static Storage/Persistent Storage&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">$3.77/GB&lt;div>*Persistent Storage&lt;/div>&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Persistent Storage, No Privacy Solution yet&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">AR&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">404&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Stratos&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Testnet&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">File Storage/Computation/Database Storage&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Static Storage/Database Storage&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">-&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Three Levels and Three Consensus to Solve the Impossible Triangle of Security, Efficiency and Decentralization&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">STRO&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">5.2&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Ceramic&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">2021&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Data Stream Storage&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Data Stream Storage/Incentive Layer&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">-&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Data Selective Encryption Ensures Privacy, User-Centric Ensures User Data Autonomous Control&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">-&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">-&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>At present, most storage solutions only implement a &amp;quot;decentralized hard disk&amp;quot;, which meets the most basic requirements, but more advanced computing requirements such as storage-based computing are not fully satisfied. These calculations include local development environment rendering , insertion and extraction of data streams, etc., these are the most commonly used and necessary functional modules in current Web2 applications. Ceramic's innovation based on data flow storage enables data rights management, version control, dynamic storage and composability, &lt;a href="https://www.thestratos.org/">Stratos&lt;/a> is trying to provide a more complete, complete set of solutions, including multiple modules such as database storage, static storage, computing and consensus. In addition, Arweave and Filecoin are also aware of the importance of computing, and are building or encouraging ecosystem-related modules, such as Filecoin [FVM has been launched to support computing on Filecoin](&lt;a href="https://filecoin.io/blog/posts/">https://filecoin.io/blog/posts/&lt;/a> introducing-the-filecoin-virtual-machine/) .&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="2-data-management">2. Data management&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Building Web3 applications on decentralized storage makes them less susceptible to external interference, breaking monopoly and power. However, storage alone is not enough. It also requires the support of technologies such as rendering computing, data processing, permission configuration and privacy protection in the storage environment to ensure the sovereignty of applications and the data sovereignty of users, so as to realize the personalization of the digital world. The rise of sovereignty. Especially access control and privacy protection issues, they should be implemented with a high-level sovereign technical solution. These levels of data in Web2 applications are stored on some specific centralized servers according to different security protection levels. Their security is guaranteed by network security, and their sovereignty is guaranteed by platforms (such as enterprise platforms, government platforms, etc.) . In this data management mode, users are subordinate to the super administrator, and the user has no rights to the data itself; in addition, data security is also subject to the centralized entity of the super administrator, such as the &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/cz_binance/status/1543700689611792386">public security data leakage incident in a certain area some time ago&lt;/a>, a super administrator leaked his private key, leaking the personal private information of hundreds of millions of people.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Web3 data management should have the following two characteristics:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Data sovereignty guarantee. This should go beyond the platform level or even the world level, and ensure the common rights of users in the digital world through world-class consensus. The guarantee in the traditional world is platform-level, and the rules come from non-consensus. A platform-level company can control all the rules and regulations and can change them at any time, thereby infringing on the individual sovereignty of users at any time.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Data Privacy Guarantee. The privacy and security of user data is mathematically guaranteed through cryptography, not through database network security. Selective encryption controlled by users is one of the basic rights of user data sovereignty.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>How Web3 data is managed depends on how the data is stored.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th style="text-align:left">Project Name&lt;/th>
&lt;th style="text-align:left">Technical Foundation&lt;/th>
&lt;th style="text-align:left">Consensus Layer&lt;/th>
&lt;th style="text-align:left">Management Mode&lt;/th>
&lt;th style="text-align:left">Privacy Protection&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">IPFS&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">IPFS&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">None&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Content Centric&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">None&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Filecoin&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">IPFS&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Content-Centric&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Third Party Project Support&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Ceramic&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">IPFS&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">None&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Arweave&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Blockchian&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Perpetual, trackable uploader&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Third-party project support&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Stratos&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Blockchain&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Yes&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Balance of the two, dynamic adjustment&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:left">Third-party project support&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>IPFS and Filecoin are content-centric, access stored content through Content ID (CID), and build third-party applications for data management on this basis, such as through [ChainSafe Files](&lt;a href="https://filecoin.io/zh">https://filecoin.io/zh&lt;/a> -cn/blog/posts/chainsafe-files/) , after the single sign-on problem can be solved in a localized way, the data can be encrypted and stored easily through asymmetric encryption. The content-centric management model makes user management difficult, and how to assign data ownership becomes more complicated. In addition to providing storage, Filecoin's ecological scalability will be much higher than other underlying layers. Especially after the launch of FVM, there may be some special tools for some vertical fields of data storage and data retrieval, which can help users to help enterprises better manage some of their data and ensure data. security, and then develop a lot of some new applications.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ceramic is also based on IPFS, but is user-centric, built on the IDX Protocol, &lt;a href="https://developers.ceramic.network/docs/advanced/standards/accounts/3id-did/">3ID DID&lt;/a> method (CIP-79) With the Ceramic-native account system, it can be used to authenticate Ceramic. Users can use the blockchain wallet to control the 3ID DID to execute transactions on the data stream and manage their own data. This is achieved by associating the DID with the data and storing it in the data model. The data model defines the schema of the user data, which is shared by all applications using the same data model.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Arweave is a one-time, permanent storage decentralized data storage project on the chain. The data is openly and transparently stored on the chain, and anyone can access it. The data stored on the chain can be browsed through the Arweave blockchain browser. The data management in this mode is exactly the same as the data on the management chain. There is no access control and &amp;quot;hot update&amp;quot; of the original data. Every time the data is updated, its index address will change. There is no problem with IPFS and Filecoin. However, the advantage is that it is very clear to which user the data belongs, which is conducive to backtracking of data rights and interests.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Stratos is also a storage based on blockchain consensus. It will maintain an index tree specifically to record the path of data storage, so as to keep track of data updates. Different from Arweave, each storage node (Resource Node) of Stratos is designed to have computing power, storage and content access control services at the same time. The project party will build a database based on the blockchain itself for dynamic data throughput. The form and management mode are close to the decentralized cloud computer.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="trend-decentralized-data-market">Trend: Decentralized Data Market&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In the case where users have data ownership, the data market is an inevitable trend, and data is circulated in it as a capital element. There has been an attempt at data market on Filecoin, &lt;a href="https://github.com/OB1Company/filehive">Fivehive&lt;/a> by the decentralized application development studio [OB1](&lt;a href="https://ob1.io/index">https://ob1.io/index&lt;/a>. html) is built and maintained, an open source marketplace that supports uploading, maintaining, purchasing and/or transferring datasets. The project Github has stopped updating and maintaining two years ago, with a high probability of failure.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="ceramics-data-model-market">Ceramic's Data Model Market&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Ceramic mentions in their &lt;a href="https://blog.ceramic.network/into-the-dataverse/">Dataverse&lt;/a> the open data model market they want to build, because data needs interoperability, it can greatly boost productivity improvement. Such a data model market is achieved through an urgent consensus on a data model, similar to the ETC contract standard in Ethereum, from which developers can choose as a function template to have an application that conforms to all the data for that data model. For now, such a market is not a trading market.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Regarding the data model, a simple example is that in a decentralized social network, the data model can be simplified into 4 parameters, namely:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;code>PostList&lt;/code>: Stores an index of user posts&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;code>Post&lt;/code>: store a single post&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;code>Profile&lt;/code>: store the user's data&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;code>FollowList&lt;/code>: Store the user's follow list&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>So how can data models be created, shared and reused on Ceramic for data interoperability across applications?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ceramic provides a data model registry ( &lt;a href="https://github.com/ceramicstudio/datamodels">DataModels Registry&lt;/a> ), an open source, community-built, reusable application data model for Ceramic repository. Here, developers can publicly register, discover, and reuse existing data models—the basis for customer-operated applications built on shared data models. Currently, it is based on Github storage, and in the future it will be decentralized on Ceramic.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All data models added to the registry are automatically published under the &lt;code>npm&lt;/code> plugin package at &lt;strong>@datamodels&lt;/strong>. Any developer can use &lt;code>@datamodels/model-name&lt;/code> to install one or more data models, making these models available to store or retrieve data at runtime using any IDX client, including DID DataStore or Self.ID.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In addition, Ceramic also built a &lt;a href="https://github.com/ceramicstudio/datamodels/discussions">DataModels Forum&lt;/a> based on Github, each model in the data model registry has its own discussion thread on this forum, the community It can be used to comment and discuss. It is also a place for developers to post their ideas on the data model to solicit community input before adding it to the registry. At present, everything is in the early stage, and there are not many data models in the registry. The data model included in the registry should become a CIP standard through the evaluation of the community, just like the smart contract standard of Ethereum, which provides a possibility for data. compositionality.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="oceans-data-trading-market">Ocean's data trading market&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Ocean Protocol has established a decentralized data service supply chain network with the data trading market as the core. The diagram below shows the main services required to create a data service supply chain, providing data, algorithms, computation, storage, analysis, and curation. These components are tied to service enforcement agreements (such as service-level agreements), secure computing, access control, and licensing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://s2.loli.net/2022/09/08/9AO7PqCBrTIv4tn.png" alt="来源：Ocean Protocol" title="Source: Ocean Protocol">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The main participating roles are data consumers, service providers, marketplaces, service publishers, validators and curators. Ocean provides a full set of data science tools. Data users can build data service pipelines on Ocean to automatically run data algorithms for data processing and value discovery. In this process, data users cannot download all datasets and see all datasets, thus protecting the datasets from being stolen, and users purchase the right to use the datasets, rather than owning the datasets.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://s2.loli.net/2022/09/08/NabTRcsoxiSmylW.png" alt="来源：Ocean Protocol" title="Source: Ocean Protocol">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In addition to this, Ocean is also partnering with other institutions to build data marketplaces, such as its partnership with Mercedes-Benz's decentralized data marketplace [Acentrik]((&lt;a href="https://acentrik.io/">https://acentrik.io/&lt;/a>) in its recently launched Enterprise Teamed up in Release.Acentrik Marketplace is powered by OceanONDA V4 smart contracts and libraries to publish data services, deploy and mint data tokens and Acentrik asset management tokens, and spend data services.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="3-data-usage-and-stack">3. Data usage and stack&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Based on the above understanding, we propose the Web3 data stack, as shown in the figure below.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>The bottom layer is where data sources are stored, including decentralized storage, on-chain and off-chain data, etc.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The second is the management applications for these data, including databases, data tables, index middleware, and data markets.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Under a certain data management paradigm, data mining can be performed, including algorithm modeling, statistical analysis and data visualization.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://s2.loli.net/2022/09/09/IhOL6tqDXw92M85.png" alt="Web3 数据堆栈 来源：Zonff Partners" title="Web3 Data Stack">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At present, most of the data usage of Web3 in the industry is on-chain data. There are endless data analysis tools and indexing tools. The huge gold mine of on-chain data has been fully tapped. Most of them are on-chain data mining, and only a few involve off-chain data. In general, the data usage link is an ETLA (Extract, Transform, Load, Analysis) process, and each node has representative items. The representative of the Extract project is The Graph, the representative of the project of the Transform (Transform) into a usable data table and the Load (Load) link is Dune and Luabsae, and the representative of the Analysis (Analysis) is Nansen and NFTGO.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On the other hand, in decentralized storage, ETLA's entire process of supporting projects is almost a desert, with only some extraction projects, and there are huge opportunities and challenges here. ** The Graph and the Ceramic community themselves are working on extracting the data on Ceramic, the founder of Orbis also tried to make a &lt;a href="https://cerscan.com/">Cerscan&lt;/a> for browsing the data on Ceramic. Arweave can already read and manage the data stored in Arweave with subgraphs through The Graph, and there are also related third-party projects on Filecoin doing this. However, the process of TLA is still unknown. The biggest reason is that the data stored in different decentralized storages is highly heterogeneous, and it is difficult to have a unified model to mine the value of these data. Among them, the most promising This step is Ceramic, because the existence of its advanced data model reduces the heterogeneity of data on Ceramic exponentially, thus making the data more available. **&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In addition to on-chain data, there are many projects trying to connect on-chain data and off-chain data. Such projects can be regarded as &amp;quot;chain reform&amp;quot; projects. Type classifications are:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Web2 data sovereignty and trading market: &lt;a href="https://dev.to/itheum/itheum-data-dex-whitepaper-ooo">Itheum&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://www.nvg8.io/">Navigate&lt;/a> , &lt;a href="https://swashapp.io/">Swash&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.getphyllo.com/">Phyllo&lt;/a> etc. This type of project mainly combines traditional Internet data with data on the chain, hoping to open up the information exchange between Web2 and Web3. Common practices are to export Web2 data and import it into a designated data pool or directly bind traditional Internet social accounts, etc. .&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Enterprise data consensus: &lt;a href="https://authtrail.com/blog/authtrail-101-with-ceo-matjaz-sobocan/">Authtrail&lt;/a>, this project integrates with the internal database of the enterprise and joins the consensus layer to achieve Tamper-proof and traceable data within the enterprise.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>On-chain and off-chain data combination: &lt;a href="https://www.spaceandtime.io/">Space and Time&lt;/a>, this project will integrate off-chain databases like Authtrail, but there is no consensus layer, more on-chain In addition, &lt;a href="https://www.pooldata.io/">Pool&lt;/a> is also doing similar things.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The usage paradigm of Web3 data is significantly different from that of Web2, which mainly lies in the way data is aggregated, that is, different types of data are stored, indexed, extracted, integrated and utilized in different ways. According to the previous classification, here are some brief summaries:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Public data: including public data and some legal person data classified in the &amp;quot;Guidelines for Cybersecurity Standards Practice - Guidelines for Data Classification and Grading&amp;quot;. As a public product, it is data that can be publicly mined for value. Access does not require permission, but user ownership can be traced to trace airdrop profits. Typical examples are on-chain data and non-encrypted application data stored in decentralized storage. (such as user posts, likes and comments, etc.). The most important upstream support for its use is for indexing applications, such as The Graph, or applications for Web3 native databases, such as Tableland.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Private data: including personal information and some legal person data classified in the &amp;quot;Guidelines for Cybersecurity Standards Practice - Guidelines for Data Classification and Grading&amp;quot;. As a data type that requires encrypted storage and certain privacy permission configuration, its access has permission and cannot be publicly obtained. If it is stored in decentralized storage and blockchain, permission-configurable encrypted storage is required. Or through other means, such as privacy technology means such as ZK, MPC and TEE. The most important upstream support for its use is database applications such as Kwil and Ceramic.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol></content></entry><entry><title type="text">Vertical Liquidity: How Value Interconnects</title><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://bubais.top/en/tech/vertical-liquidity/"/><id>https://bubais.top/en/tech/vertical-liquidity/</id><updated>2023-04-24T15:10:21+08:00</updated><published>2022-07-27T10:50:02+08:00</published><author><name>不白</name><uri>https://bubais.top/</uri><email>nowhitestar@gmail.com</email></author><rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">Some people call the blockchain the value settlement layer of the Internet, so Web3 based on blockchain technology is called the Internet of Value. The blockchain itself, as a distributed ledger, is closely associated with &amp;quot;value&amp;quot;. Its basic value is embodied in Bitcoin, a peer-to-peer electronic cash system, and with the invention of smart contracts, people have discovered Its potential is much more than that.</summary><content type="html">&lt;p>Some people call the blockchain the value settlement layer of the Internet, so Web3 based on blockchain technology is called the Internet of Value. The blockchain itself, as a distributed ledger, is closely associated with &amp;quot;value&amp;quot;. Its &lt;a href="https://cryptobriefing.com/why-bitcoin-how-money-works-today/">basic value&lt;/a> is embodied in Bitcoin, a peer-to-peer electronic cash system, and with the invention of smart contracts, people have discovered Its potential is much more than that. Blockchain technology constructs a brand-new trust system, so that anything with &amp;quot;value&amp;quot; can be transferred between networks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The high degree of decentralization of the blockchain makes it difficult to tamper with, and the global consensus recorded on the decentralized ledger is where all value is generated.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A smart contract is a code published on the blockchain. Due to the characteristics of a decentralized ledger, it is also difficult to tamper with, but it can be upgraded to a certain extent. Smart contracts solidify code constraints on the blockchain, and through global consensus, make everyone abide by the same set of governance logic. Open source free and unified standards creatively make smart contracts composable, and value is connected from then on.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tokens often refer to data units written on the blockchain defined by a contract standard. Through composability, it cooperates with other smart contracts to achieve ownership definition, profit distribution and other purposes through global consensus, thereby financializing the scene, thereby realizing multi-party governance and coordination in the scene, and exchanging value accordingly.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="the-carrier-of-value-flow">The carrier of value flow&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The value flow carrier of Web3 is the basic element supporting the entire network value flow. According to the different levels of abstraction, we divide it into three layers. The bottom layer is the medium of exchange and value storage, which is the medium of value flow; the second layer is identity, relationship, and property rights, which defines the social trust. Basic structure; the top layer is decentralized organization and society, etc., which undertakes new human collaboration methods based on the second layer.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="medium-of-exchange-and-store-of-value">Medium of exchange and store of value&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Fungible Token (FT) is the most direct value as &lt;a href="https://cryptobriefing.com/why-bitcoin-wealth-transfer/">Store of Value&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://cryptobriefing.com/why-bitcoin-wealth-transfer/">Medium of Exchange&lt;/a> vitalik.ca/general/2017/10/17/moe.html). As a value recorded on a distributed ledger, scarcity is the basis for it as a store of value, and a steady stream of buyers and sellers is the reason for the continued value of the token, and illiquid money is worthless. Therefore, as a medium of exchange, not all homogenized tokens are valuable. What needs to be established here is not only a literal global consensus based on the ledger, but also a global consensus based on psychological utility. This psychological utility, also known by some as &lt;a href="https://mirror.xyz/0xe7175fe936E9AfdEb0CACe5b88E45CEe3387ffb8/RLDoHJMElSOVPVFtVmQsgtsWCw96C1ulhPsnQGZlIhQ">internal coordination&lt;/a>, describes how digital media as a whole reflects the internal &amp;amp; organic content verification system of.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>It is the opposite of the hype-driven, narrative-driven, meme market. The main driver of investment interest is distributed peer-to-peer learning. The more memes are marketed and promoted, the more people call crypto a Ponzi scheme. But the deeper the content clues and thought snippets, the more outsiders and onlookers believe in its value.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>A typical example of this is ETH. At this stage, the mission of BTC is more of a better store of value, while ETH has slowly become the hard currency of the blockchain world. What makes this happen is not hype, narrative, and memes, but a content consensus around ETH’s distributed peer-to-peer learning. The ETH ecosystem is constantly building and developing, producing more and more utilities, such as smart contract standards, Ethereum login, and more. At the same time, as one of the most influential KOLs in the blockchain world, Vitalik continues to lead the innovation of blockchain ideas, from [blockchain governance](&lt;a href="https://vitalik.ca/general/2017/12/17/voting">https://vitalik.ca/general/2017/12/17/voting&lt;/a>. html) to &lt;a href="https://vitalik.ca/general/2021/12/06/endgame.html">Extended Endgame&lt;/a> and then to [Soul Binding](&lt;a href="https://vitalik.ca/general/2022/01/">https://vitalik.ca/general/2022/01/&lt;/a> 26/soulbound.html) etc. The ethereum souls represented by Vitalik have a very high influence in driving industry cognition and ideological improvement. These in-depth content clues and thought fragments make the outside world full of confidence in the value of ethereum.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The value flow as a homogenized token, either as a pure medium of exchange like Bitcoin, or with various utilities like Ethereum, or as a pure stable currency like USDT for online circulation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bitcoin's model is The Store of Value Hypothesis (SoV). The SoV system design can be simple and useless but needs to be strong and stable. Flow in the Internet of Value in the form of a value storage medium. This flow can be slow and low-frequency, and performance is not its first consideration. It needs to have world-class autonomy, censorship resistance, and security. This type of monetary asset is also Monero, Zcash, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Ethereum model is The Utility Hypothesis. The utility system design needs to pursue performance and functions. It is based on smart contracts and is oriented to solve real problems in real life or the network world. These utilities include, but are not limited to, transaction throughput, speed, privacy, price stability, contract flexibility and programmability, and more. Likewise, it is pursuing world-class autonomy, censorship resistance, and security, although some believe this can be compromised. This type of monetary asset also includes Bitcoin Cash, SOL, BNB, and more.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>USDT falls into the category of the utility hypothesis, which needs to maximize the utility of price stability. Its biggest feature is that it turns electronic currency into encrypted currency, so as to achieve platform-level and even world-class resistance to censorship. Anyone, anywhere, anytime, as long as they can connect to the network, can always have legal currency (such as US dollars) forever. Equivalent cryptocurrency. This impact is far-reaching. In the traditional world, there are various restrictions and obstacles in exchanging national currencies into legal currencies such as the US dollar. Stablecoins break these restrictions and make currency circulation more free. This is a highly potential scenario. This type of currency also includes USDC, DAI, BUSD, and more.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="identity-relationship-and-property-rights">Identity, relationship and property rights&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Blockchain will be the only source of truth in the digital world. Tim Sweeney of Epic Games has publicly stated that the metaverse can only exist if there is a true digital native property rights system, and the blockchain is providing such underlying capabilities. In the book Inevitably, Kevin Kelly states that &amp;quot;We cannot prevent free copying on a large scale. Doing so would not only destroy the dynamics of wealth creation, it would bring the Internet itself to a standstill. Free-flowing copies are already on the Internet. The nature of this global communication system has left its mark. Network technology requires unconstrained replication. Replicas must flow.”&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Reproduction of the digital world is inevitable, it is part of the nature of the Internet. The Internet adds value to free replicas through &lt;a href="https://www.woshipm.com/pd/454843.html">native&lt;/a> so that they become commodities that can be sold, and blockchain through global consensus provides Originally free copies define property rights and derive definitions of identity and relationship.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The technical means to achieve these include Non-Fungible Token (NFT), Soul Bound Token (SBT) and Decentralized IDentify (DID).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>NFT is &lt;a href="https://mirror.xyz/bubai.eth/KAgr16vN8IRtjHARFQ6Wx35OmgLj9Oh2qcRkiiNw_OE">a revolution in digital ownership&lt;/a>, it is defined and &amp;quot;minted&amp;quot; by smart contracts, cannot be copied and tampered with, and can be used as physical collectibles and images, music, games The &amp;quot;digital fingerprint&amp;quot; of virtual assets such as props. It defines the property rights, relationships and identities that can be exchanged. People can purchase NFTs of encrypted art works to declare their sovereignty, purchase PROOF Collective or BAYC to obtain membership in the corresponding clubs, enjoy corresponding value-added services, and can also purchase StepN’s running shoes NFT to Owning a pair of digital running shoes, you can use it to &amp;quot;run&amp;quot; and get corresponding rewards, etc. However, identity, relationship, and property rights are not all tradable, and they cannot define the totality of social ownership.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://vitalik.ca/general/2022/01/26/soulbound.html">SBT&lt;/a> implements the definition of non-tradable ownership, which is the gateway to a [decentralized society](&lt;a href="https://papers.ssrn">https://papers.ssrn&lt;/a> .com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=4105763). Identities and relationships such as personal contributions, positions, and skill certifications are non-tradable and describe a person's abilities, experiences, and identity as much as they describe a person's &amp;quot;soul&amp;quot;. It has many application scenarios, such as wallet's &lt;a href="https://vitalik.ca/general/2021/01/11/recovery.html">social recovery&lt;/a>, skill certificate, on-chain unsecured lending, decentralized governance, etc. . Combined with NFTs, they make it possible for everyone to disaggregate, trade, share, and own rights in the digital world.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>DID defines the identity of an individual in the digital world. It is the basic component of the sociality of the digital world. It makes the flow of value not only stay at the financial level, but also extends to the social credit level. Lacking a native Web3 identity, today's DeFi ecosystem cannot support activities that are ubiquitous in the real economy, such as undercollateralized loans, or simple contracts like apartment rentals. SBT is a small step in creating this kind of social identity, composability and &lt;a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=4105763">the construction of composite meaning&lt;/a> is what DID can apply to the ground The essential. Composability requires a unified standard, and the construction of composite meaning includes predictive models based on user data, composite artificial intelligence, and programmable composite privacy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The digital construction of identities, relationships, and property rights is far-reaching, allowing Web3 to transform society broadly, not just the financial system. All social structures today can thus be built in the digital world and avoid witch attacks, collusion and material over-financing.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="decentralized-organizations-and-society">Decentralized Organizations and Society&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The improvement of social trust level &lt;a href="http://www.shkxjk.com/CN/abstract/abstract3675.shtml">conducive to economic development&lt;/a>, its [influence mechanism](&lt;a href="https://books.google.com.hk/books">https://books.google.com.hk/books&lt;/a> /about/%E4%BF%A1%E4%BB%BB.html?id=FJ9LAAAACAAJ&amp;amp;redir_esc=y) is that trust directly affects the size, organization, transaction scope and transaction form of a social and economic entity, as well as the indirect effects of social The scale and intensity of productive profit-seeking activities. As the basic technology, blockchain technology has built a trustless value network system through the successful definition of identity, relationship and property rights, as well as the realization of economic incentives through tokens, and the realization of governance logic through smart contracts. This cryptography-based value network provides an organizational mechanism for a new society. These networks are bound by protocols, and protocols are bound by mathematics. Relevant parties can participate in the protocol governance in a trustless manner in accordance with the methods stipulated in the agreement, and cooperate with each other, jointly produce and distribute profits, so that for the first time, humans can coordinate a large number of related parties in a real-time and trustless manner on a global scale, greatly It reduces the cost of trust seeking of relevant parties, thereby reducing transaction costs, expanding social division of labor, production and transaction scale, stimulating economic vitality and promoting economic development.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Decentralized Autonomous Organization (DAO) is the embryonic form of this new social organization mechanism, and Decentralized Society (DeSoc) is the end point of this organizational mechanism. In 2022, a variety of DAO organizations will sprout up. The trustless collaboration within these organizations needs to improve organizational incentive rules, reward contributions and punish evildoers. Asset disposal, organizational development, etc. need to be decided through proposals and voting to ensure that the organization Everyone inside has a voice. All behaviors are made public, and the rules will be encoded into the decentralized autonomous organization through code.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the traditional world, modern civilizations such as literature, thinking, science, laws and regulations are all created on paper media. Every word written on a book records the culture and rules of the traditional world. It is difficult to tamper with and spread through books. reach a broad consensus. In the digital world, code logic is digital regulations, and the traditional Internet can only provide platform-level centralized credit and security commitments, which is highly vulnerable. Governance rules defined by blockchain technology, just like the legal provisions in the real world, need to be approved by the People's Congress. Even hackers cannot tamper with the rules. Civilization products such as literature, thinking, science, laws and regulations can exist in the digital world in new forms. It is written on the blockchain, just like written in a book, which is real, tangible and endless.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At present, many conditions are not met. The lack of infrastructure conditions makes the current DAO still maintain a strong centralized operation. At the same time, although many construction contents are open, they are difficult to trace, verify, and can be tampered with, such as records of members' contributions, certification, profit distribution, etc. These contents At present, it still requires a lot of labor costs, is inefficient, and there is still the possibility of fraud.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is still a lot of work to be done in this new form of collaboration between decentralized organizations and society. In addition to technology, there is a need for a lot of exploration and innovation in governance models.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-stack-of-the-value-network">The stack of the value network&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We try to delineate the stack of the Web3 value network:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>The bottom layer is the blockchain technology itself. It has been innovating continuously since its birth. The most mainstream view is that the first-layer blockchain network is combined with the second-layer blockchain network to modularize the blockchain. , thereby improving blockchain performance.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The second layer is the state converter and middleware, which connect the protocol built on the blockchain and the blockchain itself, state converters such as EVM and the second-layer network CariroVM, ZKEVM, ZKVM, etc. Middleware mainly includes storage, indexing, nodes and message passing. Storage solutions are constantly being upgraded and innovated, ranging from IPFS to Filecoin to Arweave to Ceramic, etc.; indexing tools are mainly the index of data on the chain (such as The Graph) and the index of storage tools (such as Kwil), the main purpose of which is to directly The data used is converted into a data set with a friendly format and easy to use; the node provides some hosting services to facilitate developers to quickly test and build their own protocols, and provide some functional APIs such as storage service APIs for developers to directly call, improve development Speed; Messaging tools are designed to open up on-chain and off-chain communication and between different blockchains, including oracles (such as Chainlink) and cross-chain protocols (such as Connext) in general.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The third layer is tokens and smart contracts, which are the continuation of value flow scenarios. Tokens can be used as value storage and exchange media, and the combination of smart contract standards and tokens makes tokens have governance utility. The code contract logic deployed on the blockchain has innovatively optimized the circulation of tokens from the perspective of liquidity, such as AMM-based DEX (such as Uniswap), collateralized lending (such as Aave), insurance and derivatives (such as Everlasting). Renewal contract exchange GMX, dYdX) and so on.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The fourth layer is the user terminal, which is the entrance to the value flow scenario, including deposit and withdrawal solutions, wallets, and Dapps. The difference between Dapp and the third-layer protocol here is mainly that it refers to the application itself, which is not composable, while the third layer mainly refers to the protocol itself, which is composable. At the same time, Dapp also has More complex interactive scenarios, such as GameFi with a lot of playable content and interactions, and SocialFi with a lot of user interaction content, are protocol-independent.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The fifth layer is the decentralized organization. It is not only the use of the Internet of Values ​​by individuals, but also the collaboration of a group of people under the Internet of Values. It requires more cooperation between people. These cooperation methods are not yet available. Not clear, we call these collaborative Dapps DAO Tools (eg Dework).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://s2.loli.net/2022/08/06/TySN4MxuabqneW6.png" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The entire value Internet stack supports the value flow scenario. There are still many technical solutions that are not perfect, and the mode of cooperation between each component is constantly changing. We realize that there may be some adjustments in the classification of some modules. And there are great innovations happening all the time in the crypto space, which may be hard to include in this chart. This is a dynamically adjusted version of the stack model for peer discussion.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="realization-scenario-of-value-network">Realization scenario of value network&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The flow of value is generated in the interaction between entities and entities, which can be people, robots, digital items or even a fixed piece of smart contract code. In this process, it involves the definition of identity, relationship and rights, resulting in sociality, and the link connecting this sociality is trust. The blockchain-centered Internet of Value is reducing the cost of trust, including investment, consumption, certification, and credit endorsement.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Transactions are the most basic realization of value networks. When it comes to transactions, we immediately think of consumer behaviors such as food, clothing, housing, and transportation and financial behaviors such as investment and loans, but blockchain is not born to undertake financial transaction scenarios in real life, it provides the truth of the digital world. In the short term, real-life legal tokens and financial transactions will not and do not need to be optimized and replaced. When we look at the protocol or application of a transaction scenario, we should think about:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Is the transaction scenario problem it solves real-world interaction or digital-native?
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>If it is a real interaction, is this issue important at this stage? Will it bring large-scale applications?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If it is digital native, why does this transaction problem need to be solved?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Is the problem it solves optimized or innovative compared to competing products?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Is its implementation safe? (such as low degree of decentralization, immature technology, etc.)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Does this specific transaction scenario need to guarantee privacy?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>……&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Pan-entertainment is a transaction-based derivation of value networks. The entertainment here includes games, fan economy, content consumption, etc. Any entertainment related to the community and financial behavior can be included. Compared with transactions, the main services of entertainment scenarios are not related to the blockchain. Blockchain will only be used in financial scenarios. However, what is often overlooked here is that the data generated by users in the process of using these applications should also be counted as financial scenarios. Data is one of the factors of production, and its capital attributes determine its financial attributes. The traditional Internet grabs a lot of benefits from the data capital provided by users. The traditional technical architecture and application logic make the centralized entities have no motivation to use the interests originally belonging to users. It is returned to users, and the lag of laws and regulations has led to the monopoly of data by centralized entities and the lack of awareness. When we look at the application of a pan-entertainment scene, we should think about:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>What kind of financialization problem is it solving?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>What does its decentralized solution look like?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>How does it handle user data?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Does it provide a new profit distribution mechanism?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>What is the distribution of power in the application? How do entities interact?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>……&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Coordination is the ultimate goal of value networks. By redesigning money, providing a multitude of public goods, and inventing governance mechanisms based on cryptoeconomics, blockchains coordinate the division of labor, production, and life of humans and goods in new ways. This is a medium- and long-term goal, although a non-standard form has been seen - a decentralized organization. Most of the current decentralized organizations are non-standard, they have strong centralized attributes, but are not as serious as corporations and governments, like a gang, with strong leaders and a common vision driven. This is mainly because people have not yet explored an efficient decentralized collaboration method. This process is an evolutionary process, and problems need to be encountered to solve problems, so that more DAO tools are born to provide weapons for decentralized coordination. When we look at an application that coordinates scenarios, we should think about:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>What kind of coordination problem is it solving?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Is it decentralized and how efficient is it?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>How does it handle user data?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>……&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The blockchain brings rules and truth to the digital world. In the modern age where the real human society and the digital virtual society are further integrated, the changes brought about by this technology are predictable. At Zonff Partners, we believe that Web3 will create a value layer for the Internet, where human beings can truly own and freely dispose of their own assets in the digital world, data will become assets that can flow, and trust between entities will be guaranteed by the network, thus forming A more efficient form of human coordination that increases productivity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thanks to Wang Xiang and Peng Yang for their suggestions and review of this article.&lt;/p></content></entry><entry><title type="text">Horizontal Liquidity: how value crosses the chain</title><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://bubais.top/en/tech/horizontal-liquidity/"/><id>https://bubais.top/en/tech/horizontal-liquidity/</id><updated>2023-04-24T15:10:21+08:00</updated><published>2022-06-16T17:53:33+08:00</published><author><name>不白</name><uri>https://bubais.top/</uri><email>nowhitestar@gmail.com</email></author><rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">The essence of liquidity is value exchange. In recent years, the market share of ethereum has been gradually declining and more and more alt-blockchains are widely used. When a new public chain/L2 ecology is formed, users create the need to migrate assets from the original ecology to the new one, as well as to transfer information across chains.</summary><content type="html">&lt;p>The essence of liquidity is value exchange. In recent years, the market share of ethereum has been gradually declining and more and more alt-blockchains are widely used. When a new public chain/L2 ecology is formed, users create the need to migrate assets from the original ecology to the new one, as well as to transfer information across chains. I refer to these cross-chain behaviors as horizontal liquidity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The need for horizontal liquidity arises when people want to be able to do things between different blockchains that could otherwise be done in the same blockchain. What prevents people from doing so then is the impediment of horizontal liquidity. The value of blockchains lies in their tamper-proof, trustless nature, and these come from a decentralized consensus that makes every transaction trustworthy, thus eliminating deception. And the core of cross-chain lies in the consensus that can be reached and transmitted (even for atomic exchange, it needs to verify the credentials for single point consensus of both parties), which is the basic value of blockchain embodied.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Consensus building and delivery requires that one blockchain be able to reliably access the state of another blockchain. Since each blockchain has its own rules, governance mechanisms, native assets, and data formats, information transfer and asset migration between blockchains is not naturally accessible. Therefore, we need a system to support the transfer of values between two or more blockchains that include assets, contract calls, proofs, or state information.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This system, which we often call a &amp;quot;bridge&amp;quot;, relies on the following components to enable state access between blockchains:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>State monitoring. There is usually a role, such as &amp;quot;Oracle&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Validator&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;Relayer&amp;quot;, which is responsible for monitoring the state on the original chain.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Message passing/forwarding. After this role receives an event, it needs to transfer the message from the original chain to the destination chain.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Consensus building. In some models, a consensus is needed between the roles monitoring the original chain in order to pass that information to the destination chain.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Message signature. The actors need to cryptographically sign the message sent to the destination chain, either individually or as part of a threshold signature scheme.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>It can be learned that the reliability of cross-chain migration depends entirely on how the above links work together. They need a verifier to ensure that there are no problems in each link, and the choice of this verifier is the main difference in the way the bridge works: some bridges use trusted systems, others use trustless systems.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="trusted-bridge">Trusted Bridge&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Such a bridge requires users to trust a third-party institution and allow the third-party institution to hold their funds. The most common type of bridge is that of a centralized exchange, such as the Binance Bridge.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The advantages of this type of bridge are obvious:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Easy to use.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Low cost. Most exchanges only charge a gasoline fee for simple conversions, no on-chain calculations.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>But they also have more obvious disadvantages:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>No control. In the process of value transfer, users must give up control of their assets.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Limited functionality. Mainly in two aspects, firstly, such bridges are only used to transfer assets and cannot be used for contract calls, proofs or state information transfer, and secondly, they can only be used to transfer CEX listed tokens.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Licensing and trust risk. Users need KYC to use such bridges and need to fully trust the bridge developer and risk that the developer may disconnect the asset bridge at any time, such as &lt;a href="https://member.fintech.global/2021/11/12/binance-suspends-dogecoin-withdrawals/#:~:text=Crypto%20currency%20exchange%20Binance%20has,version%20update%20on%20November%2011.">Binance suspends dogecoin withdrawals&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h1 id="trustless-bridge">Trustless Bridge&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>It's all about trust. De-trusting means that users don't have to worry about their assets being controlled by third parties, and it also means that such bridges can become public goods.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So what is trustless? John Adler and Mikerah Quintyne-Collins explain in their &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1904.06441.pdf">research paper&lt;/a> that &amp;quot;&lt;em>a blockchain system is trustless if and only if its state (all its state elements) is both valid and secure.&lt;/em>&amp;quot;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are several key words here, state, valid and secure.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>State. This can be understood as &amp;quot;who&amp;quot; has &amp;quot;what&amp;quot; at &amp;quot;any time&amp;quot;, which is recorded by the blockchain.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Valid. This means that the user is able to change the status of the funds for a limited period of time.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Secure. This means that the user's funds cannot be stolen and frozen forever, and only the owner can change the status of the funds.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>It is important to note that trustless does not mean no trust at all, but rather minimizing trust, which is also true for any public chain. A completely message-free cross-chain transaction would be for Alice on blockchain A to send 1000 USDC directly to her wallet address on blockchain B. Alice's wallet address on blockchain B would then receive it directly, just as in the real world I would put money from one wallet into another. This process is completely trustless because there is no third party involved, but this is impossible because different blockchains cannot directly access and modify each other's state directly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thus, &lt;a href="https://blog.li.fi/li-fi-with-bridges-trust-is-a-spectrum-354cd5a1a6d8">trustless is a spectrum&lt;/a>, and the degree of trustless is different for different mechanisms. If the trust cost of the above example with no trust at all is 0, then the trust cost of a trusted bridge is 1. The trust cost of a trustless bridge is between 0 and 1, mathematically expressed as (0, 1).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When it comes to trustless bridges, the first question we need to figure out is, &amp;quot;&lt;a href="https://blog.connext.network/the-interoperability-trilemma-657c2cf69f17">Who is the verifier of the system?&lt;/a>&amp;quot;, &lt;a href="https://blog.li.fi/what-are-blockchain-bridges-and-how-can-we-classify-them-560dc6ec05fa">different design mechanisms&lt;/a> give different answers.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>External verification. External validators are not part of any of the related blockchains and are introduced by bridges with their own unique trust assumptions. Dependent on external validators or federations, security depends on the security of the external validator/federations and different collateral mechanisms (described in detail below), such as Thorchain, Anyswap, Biconomy, Celer, Synapse, PolyNetwork, etc.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Optimistic verification. Optimistic verification relies on external verifiers, but by using honest observers to monitor operations and report fraud as verification. Its security depends on the optimistic mechanism, and since the attacker does not know at the time of the attack whether the fraud will be detected or not, this makes it impossible for the attacker to ever be sure that he will be able to successfully steal the funds, thus greatly increasing the economic cost of attacking the system, e.g. Nomad.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Local verification. The two verifiers underlying the relevant blockchain verify each other. Relying on liquidity networks, the atomic exchange process can effectively make it impossible for the validators on each chain to collude and steal funds, however liquidity networks lack cross-chain messaging capabilities and can rely on optimistic or external validation bridges to enhance the functionality of the bridge, thus reducing security, such as Connext, Hop and other atomic exchange systems.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Native verification. All validators at the bottom of the relevant blockchain are responsible for validating the system. Some native validation relies on light clients and relayers, where relayers are handled by oracle or node relayers, where the relayer transmits information from the source chain to the light client of the target chain, and the native validation node will verify the correctness of the information and trigger the corresponding smart contract, so the security depends on the relayer, such as Stargate, Cosmos IBC, Near RainbowBridge, etc.; Some native validation relies on ZKP and security depends on the relevant blockchain, such as Starkgate and other aggregation bridges.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://tva1.sinaimg.cn/large/e6c9d24egy1h3a7w545irj20v90fn0ul.jpg" alt="Bridge's trust spectrum Source: Li.Fi" title="Bridge's trust spectrum Source: Li.Fi">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From the above, it is clear that in terms of the degree of trustless, native verification &amp;gt; local verification &amp;gt; optimistic verification &amp;gt; external verification.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="native-vs-local-verification">Native vs. Local verification&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Native and local verification are originally trustless to the same extent due to their reliance on the relevant blockchain's own verifier. However, native validation cannot support generic data transfer between chains due to the use of atomic exchanges, so some other trust assumptions are often introduced to support more functionality, e.g. Hop is native validation but introduces a fast arbitrary message bridge (AMB) to enable fast bridging of optimistic aggregated funds. The protocol even relies on an externally validated bridge if no AMB exists for a given target chain. Thus, the degree of trustless: native authentication &amp;gt; local authentication.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Atomic exchange is characterized by implementing exchange operations inside a state update, typically including hash time locks and conditional transfers, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Atomic exchange across layers:&lt;/strong> The naturally connected nature of the first layer across to the second layer allows them to easily perform conditional transfers since they are bookkeeping under the same set of books. Conditional transfers, where the first segment of an operation is triggered by the second segment, are an atomic exchange that is more straightforward than hash locks (HTLCs).
There is also a second interlayer spanning between layers. Some people will look at second layer spanning as distinct from cross-chaining, when in fact they have very few differences. The only difference between Layer 2 cross-layers and cross-chains is that they are previously connected through the Layer 1 network, which allows them to communicate through conditional transfers. However, this approach is simply too expensive, requiring each cross-layer to go through the first layer network, and suffers from slow speeds and congestion. As a result, layer 2 cross-layers are often viewed as different blockchains that are not connected.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="optimistic-vs-external-verification">Optimistic vs. External verification&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Optimistic verification and external verification both essentially have a set of third-party (non-related blockchain) nodes for verification. Beyond the many differences in technical details, the core difference lies in their cryptographic economics.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>External verification (i.e., multi-signature, verifier, PoS, MPC, or threshold signature) cross-chain bridges utilize the honest majority assumption.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Optimistic verification uses the observer + fraud proof model, i.e. the verifier assumption of an honest person.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Therefore, from a trustless perspective, optimistic verification requires significantly lower trust costs than external verification.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In contrast, among external validation, there are two main economic models.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Bonded: After malicious activity occurs, node collateral is forfeited, but the system does not guarantee to compensate users for losses, e.g. &lt;a href="https://docs.polygon.technology/docs/develop/ethereum-polygon/pos/getting-started/">Polygon PoS Bridge&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Insured: After malicious activity occurs, the node collateral is reduced, and the reduced collateral is used to compensate for the user's loss, e.g. &lt;a href="https://axelar.network/">Axelar&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>From this perspective, an insured external verification bridge can relatively minimize the level of trust.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="performance-of-trustless-bridges">Performance of trustless bridges&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Different authentication mechanisms also bring different security, speed, connectivity, capital efficiency, and statefulness correlations, which are commonly used &lt;a href="https://medium.com/1kxnetwork/blockchain-bridges-5db6afac44f8">to evaluate bridge design&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Security: trust and validity assumptions, tolerance of malicious actors, security and inversity of user funds.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Speed: delay in completing transactions, and assurance of finality. There is often a trade-off between speed and security.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Connectivity: The choice of target chains for users and developers, and the different levels of difficulty in integrating additional target chains. Good connectivity means a high degree of compatibility with public chains and not easily limited by differences in consensus algorithms and data structures of different public chains.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Capital efficiency: The economics around the capital required to secure the system and the transaction costs of transferring assets.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Statefulness: The ability to transfer specific assets, more complex states, and/or perform cross-chain contract calls.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Different validation approaches have different trade-offs, each with its own advantages and disadvantages. Although there are some drawbacks to simply adding up the dimensions and calculating the total score for comparison, it seems that, as a rough guide, the total score ZKP &amp;gt; Light Clients &amp;amp; Relayers &amp;gt; Liquidity Networks = Optimistic &amp;gt; External Validators &amp;amp; Federations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://tva1.sinaimg.cn/large/e6c9d24egy1h3a7wgi6akj21150i6aby.jpg" alt="Performance of bridges with different authentication mechanisms" title="Performance of bridges with different authentication mechanisms">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>External validations excel in terms of statefulness and connectivity because they can trigger transactions, store data and allow interaction with that data on any number of target chains. Usually such third-party nodes require pledge mechanisms for security, so the capital efficiency of such bridges is minimal. In terms of security, since there are many types of externally verified bridges and different externally verified federations have different consensus algorithm security, their security cannot be generalized, but due to trust assumptions and third-party mechanisms, once the bridge is breached, the user may lose all their money and it will ripple through all the applications associated with the bridge, and their security is the lowest overall.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Optimistic verification, which performs well in terms of statefulness and connectivity, is justified in the same way as external verification. However, due to the mechanism of optimistic verification, it is more capital efficient than external verification but less than bridge designs that do not require the guarantee of a cryptographic economic mechanism. Its speed is also the lowest due to the verification window period. In terms of security, the cost of attacking an Optimistic cross-chain bridge with &lt;code>n&lt;/code> verifiers is equal to the cost of compromising or hacking &lt;code>n&lt;/code> verifiers. And relative to external verification, the cost of an attack with &lt;code>n&lt;/code> verifiers for an external verification cross-chain bridge is equal to the cost of compromising or hacking &lt;code>m&lt;/code> verifiers, where &lt;code>m&lt;/code> &amp;lt; &lt;code>n&lt;/code> . In addition, with optimistic verification, even if &lt;code>n&lt;/code> verifiers are hacked the attacker is not guaranteed to steal the funds, as long as an honest observer &amp;quot;catches the fraud&amp;quot; and revokes the attacker's access to the funds. Therefore, optimistic verification is generally more secure than external verifiers, but less secure than local verification and native verification mechanisms, where an attacker cannot steal funds at all.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Local validation (liquidity networks) excel in security and speed because the atomic exchange mechanism using hash time locks makes it impossible for funds to be stolen, and local validation without the need for universal consensus greatly increases speed. They are also more capital efficient than bonded/insured external verifiers, as capital efficiency is related to transaction flow/volume rather than security. However, because locally validated systems cannot support common data transfer between chains, their statefulness is poor, which leads to the fact that they often need to introduce other technical support to achieve more functionality, such as Hop's introduction of the Arbitrary Message Bridge (AMB) and Connext's cooperation with Nomad.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Native authentication performs very well in terms of security, capital efficiency and statefulness because it relies on the underlying trust and/or consensus mechanism of the domain to operate, and the blockhead relay system can pass any type of data without any pledge. Likewise, it must be customized for each type of domain. The Ethereum ecosystem is highly heterogeneous: ZK/optimistic aggregation, sidechains, and base chains running a large number of consensus algorithms such as ETH-PoW, Nakamoto-PoW, Tendermint-PoS, Snowball-PoS, PoA, and many others. Each of these areas requires a unique strategy to implement a natively verified interoperability system. In terms of connectivity, a native verification system using ZKP is a bit worse, since not every consensus model can be proven with zero knowledge. In terms of speed, ZKP cross-chain bridges have good low-latency properties and are also likely to be much cheaper than conventional blockhead relay systems because proving consensus does not need to happen on the chain.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>In addition, LayerZero belongs to native authentication, and its innovation, even if small, is very important, introducing a prophecy machine to enable on-demand streaming of blockheads (instead of keeping all blockheads and reducing costs) and guaranteeing security due to the addition of an independent relay system on top of the prophecy machine.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="statefulness-universal-messaging">Statefulness: Universal Messaging&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Universal messaging is the ability to call any contract on different blockchains. So why does the cross-chain approach of locally validated networks not support generic messaging?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It is actually possible for a locally validated system to implement cross-domain contract calls, but only if the function being called has some form of logical owner. For example, it is possible to trustlessly call Uniswap's swap function across chains, since anyone with an exchangeable token can call the swap function. However, it is not possible to trustlessly lock and mint NFTs across chains in local validation - this is because the logical owner of the &lt;code>mint&lt;/code> function on the destination chain should be the &lt;code>lock&lt;/code> contract on the source chain.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Intuitively, locally validated messages are sent from one contract on the chain to the same contract on another chain for function invocation through a single point of mutual validation, completing the transaction and state change within an atomic exchange process, and thus there is a logical problem of invocation; while messages of other validation methods pass the changed (fast) state through multiple points of validation, and there is no logical problem of invocation.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="connectivity-state-verification-and-consensus-reaching">Connectivity: State Verification and Consensus Reaching&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>As already talked about, it is due to the different consensus algorithms of the different chains that break connectivity. How is this understood?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Take the example of a transfer. Briefly, when a transfer occurs, a credential is generated at this point, and another chain learns that this is true than the transfer by verifying the change of credentials before it can initiate the next action. The process of generating this credential is the process of consensus algorithm, and the other chain needs to understand the credential (e.g., verify the hash) to simulate the way the credential is generated, and this is where different consensus algorithms can get in the way. At this point, the logic of ZKP is slightly different again, although the same generation algorithm can be used for ZKP, some of the consensus models are difficult to prove by zero knowledge.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="a-little-reflection-on-horizontal-mobility">A little reflection on horizontal mobility&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Horizontal liquidity refers to interoperability across chains to support messaging and asset transfer. Currently, there is no solution to the &lt;a href="https://blog.connext.network/the-interoperability-trilemma-657c2cf69f17">trilemma&lt;/a> of horizontal liquidity: trustless, scalability and generalizable. The NXTP proposed by Connext tries to build an interoperable network &amp;quot;layer 2&amp;quot; to solve this problem, based on the idea of the second layer of Ethereum, but I think the effectiveness of this solution remains to be examined.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the scalability trilemma of Ethereum, it is verification that plays the role of a mortise and tenon structural connector, so it can be developed as a modular blockchain by breaking it down with verification as the mortise and tenon into executing (computation to verify), (verification result to build) consensus and data availability (to verify).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Recently there have been voices talking about modular cross-chain bridges, which try to combine different cross-chain solutions and encapsulate them with the same interface, but this does not change the nature of the logic running under the package, and the problems that should exist remain. We need to find the mortise and tenon structure in the cross-chain problem to be able to disassemble a complex problem cleanly without breaking the original parts. Verification as a cross-chain mortise and tenon structure works because cross-chain is essentially cross-ledger bookkeeping, and the very core point is verification, but due to the differences in consensus mechanisms and data structures of different blockchains, another more core point is cross-chain message identification, because the prerequisite for verification is to identify these data messages (there is no identification problem in L2).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So how does one go about thinking about cross-chain message recognition as a cross-chain mortise and tenon structure? As mentioned above,&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>External verification, digesting cross-chain messages in an external validation federation by deploying our own smart contracts on different chains, so we have to trust this external validation federation and cannot reach trustless.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Local verification, where messaging is written in the contract as a form of logical structure (atomic exchange), which directly leads to its lower connectivity and very low statefulness, it can only deliver an exchange logic and not a generic ledger change type of message and cannot reach generalizability.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Native verification, messages are delivered directly in the original data structure, reach the target blockchain, and then the data stored in the original blockchain data structure is deconstructed, computed, and validated. This requires a codified medium in between to be able to understand and translate the data structure of the two blockchains. Different consensus algorithms pose a number of challenges, and even ZKP, which is the &amp;quot;silver bullet&amp;quot; for verification, encounters translation problems here. Therefore, it is difficult to make native verification scalable.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>There are about two paths I can think of to solve this problem: one is the emergence of ZKP algorithms that support common consensus algorithms; the other is to build a message recognition middleware by non-intermediate consensus.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Feel free to discuss any immature thoughts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Many thanks to Yang Peng and Xiang Wang for proofreading this paper.&lt;/p></content></entry><entry><title type="text">Ethereum's ZK Rollup Era</title><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://bubais.top/en/tech/ethereum-zk-rollup-era/"/><id>https://bubais.top/en/tech/ethereum-zk-rollup-era/</id><updated>2023-04-24T15:10:21+08:00</updated><published>2022-04-22T21:51:33+08:00</published><author><name>不白</name><uri>https://bubais.top/</uri><email>nowhitestar@gmail.com</email></author><rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">Ethereum is about to enter its Layer 2 era, and ZK Rollup is one of the best solutions among all L2 scaling technologies. What kind of sparks can zero-knowledge proof technology and aggregate expansion technology create? How is ZK Rollup better than other scaling technologies? How can it be adopted quickly? From the perspective of investment, how to capture the value of the ZK Rollup era, and what kind of innovative applications will it produce?</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="why-focus-on-zero-knowledge-zk-rollup">Why focus on Zero-Knowledge (ZK) Rollup?&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>For a brief introduction to ZK and ZK Rollup technology, you can refer to my previous article.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://mirror.xyz/bubai.eth/CfIJX6ASjERg-MdYccN7QYf0T88Ey3fCk-F7MNLtq9I">ZK Rollup: The Future of Ethereum Scaling&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Zero-Knowledge cryptography has been called one of the most underrated technologies of our generation. Unlike the overwhelming news coverage of topics like artificial intelligence and big data, there is little media attention to zero-knowledge technology. Nonetheless, the technology is still a great breakthrough, bringing valuable privacy guarantees to this era of big data where personal information has nowhere to hide.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Zero-knowledge cryptography is a broad topic, but in this article, we will only focus on one area most relevant to blockchains: zero-knowledge proofs. A zero-knowledge proof is a non-interactive, zero-knowledge proof of knowledge that assumes two parties: a prover and a verifier. The prover wants to prove to the verifier that they know some information without revealing what it is. At the same time, the validator will look at the proof and accept or reject it. These schemes have three properties:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Integrity - any valid result can justify a given program&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Robustness - no dishonest actor can create valid proofs&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Zero knowledge - the verifier knows nothing about the &lt;em>input&lt;/em> of the proof, only the result&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>In the realm of blockchains, which are publicly visible on all data chains, this proof of a statement without revealing its truth is a powerful primitive. Whether for individuals, enterprises or governments, this technology can solve many real pain points, such as &lt;a href="https://zeroknowledge.fm/zero-knowledge-cryptography-the-next-digital-revolution/">Protecting user data, designing sensitive systems or contracts, proving fairness in the distribution of public goods, and enabling more efficient and economical government agencies&lt;/a>。&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the field of blockchain, in addition to privacy protection, the most eye-catching application is ZK Rollup, the expansion scheme of Ethereum. &lt;a href="https://ethereum-magicians.org/t/a-rollup-centric-ethereum-roadmap/4698">Ethereum is currently embracing a rollup-centric scaling solution&lt;/a>, it represents the optimal trade-off between decentralization, security, and scalability. Essentially, the Ethereum upgrade will make the network more scalable, sustainable and secure.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The expansion plan of Ethereum is divided into on-chain expansion and off-chain expansion.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On-chain scaling technology is an upgrade to the base layer of the blockchain to improve scalability. Ethereum's long-term on-chain scaling solution is called sharding, which actually splits the base layer into 64 chains with shared security secured by the beacon chain.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Off-chain scaling refers to scaling solutions that use an external execution layer instead of the base layer. These Layer 2 or &amp;quot;L2&amp;quot; are auxiliary layers that sit on top of the base layer and provide more transactional capabilities to the entire blockchain. The L2s solution embraced by Ethereum is Rollup, which can bring the following features:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>With roll up, Ethereum can go from about 25 to 3,000 TPS without sacrificing security;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>With roll up, user funds cannot be stolen or censored (as is the case on some sidechains);&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Users can always access data on L1, and no one can prevent users’ funds from safely withdrawing from the roll up at any time.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>There are two (main) types of rollups in current solutions: ZK Rollup (ZKRU) and Optimistic Rollup (OR).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="optimistic-and-zero-knowledge-method-comparison">Optimistic and Zero Knowledge method comparison&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Optimistic Rollup is a more mature solution than ZKRU. Products from Optimstic and Arbiturm are already available to Ethereum developers. However, due to the use of the fraud proof mechanism, its withdrawal time and security are currently debatable, and its cost optimization is slightly inferior to ZK. The weaknesses of ZK Rollup are basically technical problems. With a large number of excellent developers investing in related research, most people including Vitalik agree that ZK Rollup will be a better expansion solution in the future. Comparing the two, &lt;a href="https://w3hitchhiker.mirror.xyz/7dwD76ZZIlR7ep731K6y9vTTuXGHOojxWSnkXKzqPzI">the gas cost and TPS of each solution are as follows&lt;/a>：&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://tva1.sinaimg.cn/large/e6c9d24egy1h2bizskocfj216u0n4q78.jpg" alt="untitled" title="The cost of each of the four methods Source: Xiang｜W3.Hitchhiker，The premise of the above calculation is that the current Eth price is 2500u, the block gas limit is 30000000, the gas cost is 30Gwei, and the average block time is 13 seconds. The limit TPS refers to the corresponding operating environment occupying all Ethereum block space (in the proof verification Costs 500,000 gas), ordinary TPS means that the corresponding operating environment occupies 1/3 of the block space of all Ethereum.">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In terms of efficiency and cost, the ZK scheme is more efficient than the OR scheme, with higher TPS and lower costs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In terms of time cost, and due to the fraud proof mechanism, withdrawals on Optimtisc Rollup require a submission period of 7-14 days for others to falsify potential malicious behavior, although there are already Optimstic Rollup solutions such as Boba Network. Proposed liquidity pool mechanism to reduce withdrawal period.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In terms of compatibility, both Optimistic and ZK face the problem of accommodating complex EVM contract invocation operations, but Optimistic is easier to achieve this. OR solutions including Arbitrum, Optimism have EVM-compatible virtual machines, allowing them to process all transactions on the main chain of Ethereum.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One of the main issues limiting the development of ZK Rollup is EVM compatibility. At the beginning of the EVM design, the developer did not expect to use ZK technology in the future. Therefore, it is almost impossible to generate usable zero-knowledge proofs through EVM operations, thus giving rise to the need for ZK-EVM. So far there is no publicly available ZK-EVM solution. However, the zkSync 2.0 public testnet was officially launched at the end of February, which is also the first EVM-compatible ZK Rollup on the Ethereum testnet. Perhaps the large-scale practical use of ZK Rollup will come sooner than we expect.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Why is EVM compatibility so difficult for ZK?
Most of the existing ZK Rollup solutions can only support simple payment and swap scenarios. The reason is that zkEVM not only needs to normally execute the bytecode of the smart contract, but also needs to generate a Proof to indicate that the state has been updated correctly after the transaction is reached. It’s difficult for the two to be compatible due to t&lt;a href="https://hackmd.io/@yezhang/S1_KMMbGt">he design of EVM and the algorithm principles of ZK Proof&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>In terms of security, the security of OR comes from economics where a reasonable incentive mechanism must be designed to drive a group of verifiers on the main chain to monitor the submitter at any time and be ready to submit fraud proofs. The submitter, on the other hand, must pay the price for the evil node by staking. Meanwhile, the security of ZK comes from mathematics or cryptography which can be trustless. The guarantees provided by mathematics and cryptography are far more reliable than the optimistic belief that human nature cannot be evil.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In comparison, the &lt;a href="https://mirror.xyz/0x3D5FE39342e661776bb5273521F52E99B624288c/NFOsWYCb2eVk612VSnrrCsoKcwI_EMObp_q9uNKa4uA">pros and cons&lt;/a> of ZK Rollups are as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>PROS&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Less data contained in each transaction increases the throughput and scalability of L2 with the benefits of greater scalability and reduced transaction costs compared with Optimistic Rollups;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There is no need for anyone to monitor ZKR;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Do not require a dispute window like Optimistic Rollups, which can reduce the withdrawal time from about two weeks to minutes;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Privacy is enabled by default.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>CONS&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The difficulty in computing zero-knowledge proofs will require data optimization to get maximum throughput;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Initially setting up and integrating into the Ethereum network is more difficult than Optimistic Rollups.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Relatively speaking, the weaknesses of ZK Rollup are basically technical issues. It is believed that these problems will be solved as a large number of outstanding developers are devoting themselves to relevant research. Most people including Vitalik agree that ZK Rollup will be a better scaling solution in the future.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="what-is-the-landscape-of-the-zk-rollup-scalability-solution">What Is the Landscape of the ZK Rollup Scalability Solution?&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="zk-rollups-players-comparison">ZK Rollups Players Comparison&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There are two major players in the ZK Rollup technology area: &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/zksync">zkSync&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/StarkWareLtd">StarkWare&lt;/a>。&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Some of the &lt;a href="https://news.ethereum.cn/Layer2/zksync-vs-starkware">major differences&lt;/a> between the two players in terms of team, technology, data availability, financing and supporters, current products and roadmaps are shown directly in the table below.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>&lt;/th>
&lt;th>StarkWare&lt;/th>
&lt;th>zkSync（Matter Lab）&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Team&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Established in May 2018. Its core members include a former Chief Scientist of Zcash and professors at Technion Israel Institute of Technology&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Established in December 2019. Alex G. is its co-founder&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Technology&lt;/td>
&lt;td>zk-STARKs&lt;/td>
&lt;td>zk-SNARKs（like PLONK）&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Data Availability&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Off-chain solution: Volition&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Off-chain solution: zkPorter (based on Volition architecture, more decentralized)&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Financing and Supporters&lt;/td>
&lt;td>A seed round funding of 6 million USD in May 2018 (Pantera/Naval/Vitalik) &lt;br> A Series A funding of 30 million USD in October 2018 (Paradigm/Sequoia/Cb Ventures) &lt;br> A Series B funding of 75 million USD in March 2021 (Paradigm/3AC/Alameda) &lt;br> A Series C funding of $50 million in November 2021 (Paradigm/3AC/Alameda) &lt;br> Supporters: Ethereum Foundation members, prominent investment institutions&lt;/td>
&lt;td>A Series A funding of 6 million in March 2021 (Binance/Cb Ventures/AAVE/Balancer/Curve) &lt;br> A Series B funding of 50 million in November 2021 (a16z/Placeholdxr/Crypto.com, etc.) &lt;br> Supporters: comparatively not so many famous investors&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Current Products&lt;/td>
&lt;td>StarEx、StarkNet、Volition、Validium&lt;/td>
&lt;td>zkSync、zkPorter&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Roadmap&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Planets-&amp;gt; Constellations-&amp;gt; Universe&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Scalable Payments -&amp;gt; Smart Contracts -&amp;gt; Privacy -&amp;gt; Censorship Resistance&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Team. StarWare have more academic professionals. Its team is composed of world-class cryptographers and scientists who have been pioneers and innovators in the zero-knowledge field for many years. They have published many academic papers, which are in the process of turning into a real-world product, StarkWare. Meanwhile, there is not much information about zkSync team. From the product launch, it’s indicated that the team is cross-professional and highly efficient.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Technology. StarkWare is still a better choice. It provides blockchain finality, which means it has the optimal capital efficiency. Besides, the &lt;a href="https://www.geekmeta.com/article/3421070.html">main advantages&lt;/a> of STARK are as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>1.StarkWare invented and built its own ZK-STARK system, while zkSync’s technology stack was built by someone else (PLONK, built by Aztec). This also means that StarkWare is more capable of mastering and improving technology.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>StarkWare already has several systems running in the production environment, which use a Turing-complete programming language called Cairo, which is readily available; while Matter Labs has only one simple payment system in the production environment, and no Turing-complete language is available.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>StarkWare is faster, more secure (in a cryptographic sense), transparent (no trust settings required) and post-quantum secure; while the core technology used by Matter Labs (built by another team) is slower, requires trust settings, and can be breached by quantum computers.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Data availability (DA). StarkWare invented the Volition system to solve DA problems. Volition allows end-users to choose between the rollup solution (on-chain data availability) and the validium solution (off-chain data availability) for each transaction. ZkSync uses the zkPorter technology based on Volition. The main difference between Volition and zkPorter is: in the Volition solution, users can choose the data storage method based on each transaction, while in zkPorter solution, users can choose the transaction settlement method based on each account (zkPorter accounts can only be accessed through off-chain data-available ways to make transactions). In addition, zkPorter’s off-chain DA system is more decentralized, because its DA is motivated by Guardian, actuated by zkSync native tokens to provide security, rather than a centralized “DAC”.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Financing and supporters. StarkWare is valued at 2 billion USD and is in the process of raising a Series D funding worth approximately 6 billion USD. This is a world-class financing process, attracting many famous investors. Some tycoons and members of Ethereum Foundation have been involved. Vitalik itself has also reviewed most of the articles published by StarkWare. Compared with StarkWare, zkSync has fewer prominent investors, and it looks like large-scale DeFi/CEX encrypted family financing. Each of these projects is well-recognized, and together they can form a good ecosystem. It’s important to note that the success of ZK Rollup will depend heavily on the addition of the DeFi protocol and the direct integration with CEX.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Current products and roadmap. In June 2020, StarkWare first launched StarEx, which represents the “Planets” phase of their roadmap and allows the creation of permissioned, application-specific ZK Rollup supported by Cairo and STARKs, such as &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dydxprotocol">dydx&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Immutable">Immutable&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/deversifi">Deversifi&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://sorare.com/?action=signin">Sorare&lt;/a>. They are the four main applications supported by the production version of StarkEx. As of March 2022, StarkEx has processed 134 million transactions, and its cumulative transaction volume amounts to $490 billion and the Total Value Locked hit $1.1 billion.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://tva1.sinaimg.cn/large/e6c9d24egy1h2bj0upigbj20iw097jry.jpg" alt="StarkWare 路线图 来源：StarkWare" title="StarkWare Roadmap Source: StarkWare">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On November 29, 2021, they released the Alpha version of the mainnet of StarkNet, which is rapidly moving towards the “Constellations” phase of the roadmap. StarkNet is the general ZK Rollup that we expect to be permissionless and multi-application. As of March 2022, the StarkNet testnet Goerli has generated 1.4 million transactions and 45,000 were made on the mainnet. In terms of contract deployment, there are 26,000 contracts on the testnet Goerli and 1,600 contracts on the mainnet.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Initially, StarkNet will be driven by a centralized prover, and applications will need to apply for a whitelist to be deployed sequentially, just like what Optimism did. They plan to develop the ecosystem and gradually decentralize StarkNet to achieve the “Universe” phase of the roadmap.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The roadmap for zkSync can be summarized as the following 4 steps. The first phase corresponds to the zkSync 1.0 launched in June 2020, which is roughly equivalent to a ZK Rollup without smart contract integration. Users can send and receive tokens but this lacks composability. Many promising projects have been already deployed on zkSync 1.0.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://images.mirror-media.xyz/publication-images/wn63t_kZgq73Qtgrzt0JR.png?height=206&amp;amp;width=837" alt="zkSync 路线图 来源：Matter Lab" title="zkSync Roadmap Source：Matter Lab">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The second phase of the roadmap started with the launch of zkSync 2.0 on the mainnet, which includes everything we expect: a fully EVM-compatible ZK Rollup with smart contract composability. zkSync 2.0 was initially planned to be launched on the mainnet in August but was delayed due to &lt;a href="https://blog.matter-labs.io/zksync-2-0-developer-update-d25417f16446">some technical difficulties&lt;/a>. These issues are now being tested on the testnet and are gradually being resolved. In October, zkSync revealed some of its recently completed technical details and deployed an AMM-like testnet (uniswap) to verify its EVM compatibility. To ensure the compatibility of LLVM/Solidity, Matter Labs delays its launch, which may sound depressing at the beginning. However, it will help every Ethereum tool to achieve local integration on zkSync 2.0.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="advantages-of-zk-rollup">Advantages of ZK Rollup&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The ZK Rollup solution can bring &lt;a href="https://mp.weixin.qq.com/s/r7cNMWYPP-9sqjLcKz64Aw">unique advantages&lt;/a> such as privacy protection, scalability preserving and cross-chain application implementation.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Privacy is one of the advantages and features of ZK Rollup.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Permissionless blockchains can achieve computational completeness without trusting third parties, but they come at a cost in terms of scalability and privacy. Since the 1980s, theoretical work on the proof system such as zero-knowledge proofs, interactive proofs, and probabilistically checkable proofs has elucidated ways to address these two issues and embodied them in practical applications.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol start="2">
&lt;li>Scalability gives developers almost unlimited computing power theoretically.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>This makes it possible to port over all the ecologies on the Internet. For example, matchmaking games were previously difficult to develop on Ethereum, but ZK Rollup can change that. In addition, the supercomputing power coupled with the characteristics of the blockchain can also create many new applications.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol start="3">
&lt;li>The cross-chain application is one of the representatives of ZK Rollup. StarkNet has a very diverse range of bridging functions.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Developers can send any load (not transfers) from L1 to L2, that is, deploy the head of the dApp on L2 where governance or game operations can be performed at a lower cost, while sending instructions to the liquidity of L1. It's like using L2 as the brain and L1 as the muscle.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="limitations-of-zk-rollup">Limitations of ZK Rollup&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Although ZK Rollup is a very good solution for Ethereum scaling, its applications are still accompanied by some risks, such as liquidity fragmentation, reduced composability due to communication difficulties and technology barriers, and centralization risks.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>The problem of liquidity fragmentation has become increasingly prominent in the current multi-chain world and is not specific to ZK Rollup applications.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Due to the existence of multiple technology solutions, the number of rollup networks will increase in the future, which will lead to more severe liquidity fragmentation. The good news is that there are many cross-chain communication technology solutions that address this issue, such as Layerzero's StarGate (note that StarGate does not support ZK Rollup at the moment) launched in March 2022. Under the premise of ensuring security, LayerZero is bringing us an “omni-chain future”, including state sharing, unified bridge liquidity, cross-chain lending, Swap, and multi-chain revenue aggregators.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol start="2">
&lt;li>The composability problem is mainly reflected in the interaction between the main chain dapp and the sub-chain dapp.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Each new protocol built on Ethereum is like a Lego block on which other protocols can easily be built, which is one of &lt;a href="https://future.a16z.com/how-composability-unlocks-crypto-and-everything-else/">the reasons why DeFi is growing rapidly&lt;/a>. If the communication and contract standard issues cannot be solved, then dapps on sub-chains need to rebuild their own ecologies, which creates abigger waste of resources. Communication mechanisms and corresponding contract standards are needed not only between sub-chains and main chains, but also between sub-chains and sub-chains.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol start="3">
&lt;li>The centralization risk is mainly due to the fact that the sequencer responsible for executing, sorting, compressing and packaging transactions in current Rollup solutions is a more centralized role. Rollup must address the centralization issue if it is to further improve security.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h1 id="what-does-the-future-of-scaling-look-like">What Does the Future of Scaling Look Like&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://ethereum-magicians.org/t/a-rollup-centric-ethereum-roadmap/4698">The scaling roadmap of Ethereum&lt;/a> describes the scaling scenario focusing on Optimistic Rollup in the short term and sharding + ZK Rollup in the medium and long term.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In general, &lt;a href="https://www.panewslab.com/zh/articledetails/D56636383.html">Rollup is undoubtedly the best option for Ethereum scaling&lt;/a> due to its impressive characteristics of security and scalability. Although it takes time to solve technical problems in terms of programmability, Rollup is a very ideal scaling technology in the medium and long term. The combination of Ethereum sharding and ZK Rollup will break the so-called Impossible Triangle. At the same time, the launch of zkEVM can support programmability and help developers move to L2 more easily.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>In the medium to long term, ZK rollups will win out in all use cases as ZK-SNARK technology improves. — Vitalik Buterin&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Nevertheless, there are many issues to be addressed before ZK Rollup can be actually adopted on a large scale, including &lt;a href="https://hackmd.io/@yezhang/S1_KMMbGt">technology&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://future.a16z.com/go-to-market-in-web3">GTM &lt;/a>(Go to Market) and &lt;a href="https://future.a16z.com/community-%E2%89%A0-marketing-why-we-need-go-to-community-not-just-go-to-market/">GTC&lt;/a> (Go to Community).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="technology-issues">Technology Issues&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The technology issues of the ZK Rollup have been briefly explained above, and some details are added here.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Regarding compatibility, technology problems of ZK Rollup mainly lie in the fact that it is not developer-friendly, resulting in limited functionality. Previously, it was difficult to build generic DApps mainly due to the following two reasons.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>First, if you want to develop DApp on ZK Rollup, you are required to write all your smart contract logic in a special language (i.e. &lt;a href="https://tlu.tarilabs.com/cryptography/r1cs-bulletproofs/mainreport.html#rank-1-constraint-systems">R1CS&lt;/a>). The syntax of the required language is complex. Furthermore, you have to possess comprehensive expertise in zero-knowledge proofs.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Second, ZK Rollup does not support composability, which means different ZK Rollup applications cannot interact with each other on L2. This quality greatly undermines the composability of DeFi applications.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>There are two ways to build a generic DApp in ZK Rollup. One is to build application-specific circuits (ASIC) for different DApps, which is the path taken by ZK Rollup in its early stages, corresponding to the “Planets” phase of StarkWare where applications cannot interact with each other. The other way is to build a general “EVM” circuit for smart contract execution, on which StarkWare and zkSync have made great progress.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The development of StarkWare is in the “Constellations” phase for the time being. In September 2021, StarkWare announced the launch of the general ZK Rollup that is permissionless, multi-application, and supportive to smart contracts through Cairo. Meanwhile, the development of zkSync is also in the second stage. In February 2022, the zkSync 2.0 testnet was launched. Continuous testing ensures LLVM/Solidity compatibility for full EVM compatibility and smart contract composability.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note: StarkWare and zkSync adopt two completely different technology solutions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>StarkWare uses &lt;a href="https://medium.com/starkware/starknet-alpha-2-4aa116f0ecfc">Cairo, a brand new Turing-complete programming language&lt;/a>, and works with OpenZeppelin to develop standardized contracts, just as they did with Ethereum, which means they adopt a new contract standard for composability. It’s certainly a bold decision, as it will significantly increase the entry cost for developers. For now, Nethermind’s Warp team &lt;a href="https://medium.com/nethermind-eth/warp-your-way-to-starknet-ddd6856875e0">is helping&lt;/a> developers convert ERC-20 contracts from EVM bytecode to StarkNet contracts and deploy them on StarkNet. The project is progressing rapidly, and its next goal is to move arbitrary smart contracts from Yul to Cairo.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On the other hand, &lt;a href="https://mirror.xyz/kuiqian.eth/FW6gE79ksYDgfrDOhW9zse-bGhLBzaMizIlid3iKZ8Q">zkSync uses zkEVM solution for EVM compatibility&lt;/a>. For zkEVM, there are two major implementation strategies at the moment.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Directly supports the existing set of EVM opcodes, which is fully compatible with the set of Solidity opcodes. This strategy is used by Hermez and the Ethereum Foundation zkEVM.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Maintaining Solidity compatibility by redesigning a new virtual machine that is ZKP-friendly and adaptive to EVM development tools. This strategy is mainly used by zkSync.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Overall, the first strategy has better compatibility and higher security, but needs more work, which is used by Hermez; the second strategy is more flexible with less work but requires extra effort in adaptation, which is used by zkSync. zkSync has developed two compiler front-ends for zkEVM at the same time: Yul and Zinc. zkSync chose LLVM to build its own compiler. The LLVM/Solidity compatibility issue is the major reason behind the &lt;a href="https://blog.matter-labs.io/zksync-2-0-developer-update-d25417f16446">failure to launch&lt;/a> zkSync 2.0 as scheduled in August 2021, which is also the issue that is currently being focused on during the launch of the zkSync 2.0 testnet.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Using Cairo makes StarkWare seem to be less compatible. Is this the weakness of StarkWare? It is not.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>StarkWare uses the Cairo language to port the smart contract logic to Rollup. Although the new language somewhat increases the entry cost for developers, many features of Cairo allow ZK to integrate more elegantly into the blockchain ecosystem.For example, Cario has an accompanying Algebraic Intermediate Representation (AIR) visualization tool to view the details of proofs, securely and credibly generate zk-STARK proofs to ensure computational completeness, and the language is designed to be neater and more logically in line with mathematical proofs, and it has a complete tool chain as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In addition, Cairo also &lt;a href="https://medium.com/starkware/hello-cairo-3cb43b13b209">increases security&lt;/a>. Cairo’s AIR is relatively simple, which leads to low efficiency and low amortized costs for both the on-chain verifier and the off-chain proving service. Besides, auditing a single simple AIR is safer than auditing multiple complicated application-specific AIRs. As a result, with Cairo, we can rely on a single Verifier smart contract; there is no longer a need to deploy a Verifier for every application used.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note the security implication of this property: a single set of audits for this one contract protects any application from the proof system risk since it only audits the business logic. As for the business logic, it’s much easier to understand and audit the correctness of codes than it is to comprehend application-specific AIR. Cairo cannot solve the problem of possible bugs in contracts faced by EVM currently. However, &lt;a href="https://multicoin.capital/2022/03/15/move-move-move/?mc_cid=43fd88cdd6&amp;amp;mc_eid=0b68dd5aad">some people&lt;/a> are trying to fix it.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="go-to-market-issues">Go-to-Market Issues&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>ZK Rollup gains the market in much the same way as public chains named “Ethereum killers”. StarkWare is centralized and is promoting decentralization right now, while zkSync is open source and decentralized (not at a high level), but neither of them has a token. Similarly, Optimism and Arbitrum, the other two players in the Rollup technology area, have no tokens.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>zkSync will launch a token as confirmed by their source codes. StarkWare and Arbitrum have no public statements, but Optimism has launched the token recently.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Nonetheless, issuing tokens is necessary for L2s to promote decentralization and gain the market. &lt;a href="https://newsletter.banklesshq.com/p/rollup-tokens-are-coming?s=r">Tokens, as a good incentive tool, can also help to better govern the community&lt;/a>. The main obstacles to issuing tokens are the immaturity of L2s cross-chain bridges and the unsettled EVM compatibility.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>According to the organizational structure and economic incentive model of Web3, A16Z defines the &lt;a href="https://future.a16z.com/go-to-market-in-web3">GTM matrix&lt;/a> as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://tva1.sinaimg.cn/large/e6c9d24egy1h2bj1p5k5dj21bu0u076h.jpg" alt="Web3 走向市场矩阵 来源：a16z" title="Web3 GTM Matrix Source:a16z">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>They argued that the Go to Market (GTM) strategy of Web3 is hugely different from that of Web2. The most innovative part is the introduction of tokens and the emergence of the new organizational structure Decentralized Autonomous Organization (DAO). GTM differs in each of the quadrants and can span everything from traditional web2-style strategies to emerging and experimental strategies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Metrics that measure whether Layer1/Layer2 gains the market include the number of Github stars, protocol developers, project integrations, protocol forks, and TVL.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://tva1.sinaimg.cn/large/e6c9d24egy1h2bj2657llj21kw0fo0u4.jpg" alt="L1 公链走向市场矩阵 来源：a16z" title="L1 Public Chain GTM Matrix Source: a16z">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here, there is no way to compare StarkWare as it is not open source. Looking at the data in March 2022, the situation of zkSync, Optimism and Arbitrum are as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>When it comes to Github stars, zkSync comes out on top. ZkSync has 1,300 stars, slightly higher than Optimism’s 900 stars and Arbitrum’s 700 stars.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When it comes to the number of protocol developers on Github, Optimism comes in first. zkSync has 43 developers, Optimism 66, and Arbitrum 36.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When it comes to the number of protocol forks on Github, Arbitrum has a slightly higher number of 355, while the forks of zkSync and Optimism are quite close, being 292 and 303 respectively.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When it comes to TVL, Arbitrum is far ahead with $3.41 billion at present, while zkSync and Optimism stand at $148 million and $562 million respectively.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>In comparison, the more successful Ethereum “alternative chain” Solana has 7,700 Github stars, 1,800 forks, 305 contributors and a TVL of $7.46 billion.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It can be seen that the present Rollups are far from being called a market winner, and there is still a lot of work to be done. The most important is to get more project integrations, since more adoption will attract more developers, thus building better eco-projects, getting more users and attracting more funding. To achieve these goals, the project side is required to Go to Community (GTC).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="go-to-community-issues">Go-to-Community Issues&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://future.a16z.com/community-%E2%89%A0-marketing-why-we-need-go-to-community-not-just-go-to-market/">It is argued&lt;/a> that the key difference between the incentives in GTM and GTC strategy can be summarized as the difference between value capture and value creation. For a product, it is its users that make up the community, while for a blockchain or a protocol, it is the applications that adopt it that make up the community. Therefore, it may be more accurate to use Ecosystem instead of Community here. Now, with the launch of StarkNet Alpha and zkSync 2.0 testnet, ZK Rollup technology has been adopted rapidly, and their ecosystems are also expanding. The ecosystems of the two technologies have been sorted as shown below.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Currently, with the launch of the StarkNet Alpha and zkSync 2.0 testnets, ZK Rollup technology is rapidly being adopted, and the ecosystems of both are expanding. Some people have organized the ecology of the two major technologies as shown below.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://tva1.sinaimg.cn/large/e6c9d24egy1h2bj2eewsbj21gs0u07dh.jpg" alt="StarkWare Landscape 来源：ZK_Daily" title="StarkWare Landscape Source: ZK_Daily">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://tva1.sinaimg.cn/large/e6c9d24egy1h2bj2mr8ayj21gf0u0qch.jpg" alt="zkSync Landscape 来源：ZK_Daily" title="zkSync Landscape Source: ZK_Daily">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The two ecosystems have comparable levels of prosperity. It can be seen that zkSync is supported by more cross-chain, DeFi and wallet applications, while there is a more prosperous Games &amp;amp; NFTs ecosystem on StarkWare.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For an L1s/L2s ecosystem, &lt;a href="https://newsletter.banklesshq.com/p/liquidity-is-bandwidth">liquidity is equivalent to bandwidth&lt;/a>, connecting different application scenarios to form a larger network, i.e. the Internet of Value. The definition of liquidity over here is the value exchange between different applications. When liquidity is good, there is less value loss; and when it is poor, there is more value loss. In addition, when there is no value exchange between different applications, there is no liquidity. An ecosystem is only functioning when its liquidity can run through the whole process, like the Ethereum ecosystem where every application based on Ethereum can be valued and exchanged through Ethereum.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I divide the liquidity in the ecosystem into horizontal and vertical liquidity. In L2s, the role of the bridge is to bridge between different Rollups horizontally. Recently, there is an innovative way called LayerZero, which innovates the liquidity bridging way of traditional bridges and brings better security and trustlessness. The vertical liquidity mainly lies in different applications. End Users connect to the whole ecosystem through Wallet. Sometimes they top up and buy cryptocurrency through Payment to get value and exchange value in different applications. Sometimes intermediate exchange is required through Marketplace apps.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://tva1.sinaimg.cn/large/e6c9d24egy1h2bj2v0ef5j20ma0f9q3p.jpg" alt="L2 生态价值流动图" title="L2 Eco-value Flow Diagram">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At present, in each liquidity node, StarkWare and zkSync have corresponding applications deployed, most of which are in the testing phase, and their ecosystems are compared in the chart below.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://tva1.sinaimg.cn/large/e6c9d24egy1h2bj34ji7lj21gx0u0gtw.jpg" alt="zkSync 和 StarkWare 生态对比 来源：ZK_Daily" title="zkSync and StarkWare Ecosystem Comparison Source: ZK_Daily">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Go to Community (Ecosystem), first of all, needs to be able to open up vertical liquidity internally, which requires support for composability so that there is a unified standard in the ecosystem that enables permissionless mutual integration between different application protocols just as Lego blocks. This is easy to do on Ethereum, but due to the zero-knowledge proof issue, both StarkWare and zkSync have worked very hard to solve this problem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The prerequisite for a vibrant community (ecosystem) is to have good horizontal liquidity, which requires the support of useful bridges that can bridge the liquidity of Ethereum at a low cost and, more importantly, can easily communicate with other L2 solutions or even L1 solutions. A fast (high TPS), low cost (low fees) and secure blockchain are naturally attractive for both applications and users. The lower the migration cost, the more attractive the ecosystem is to both applications and users.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The necessary condition for a community (ecosystem) to take off is the emergence of the killer app that draws a large number of users and capital in. This cannot be achieved only through high APY, token airdrops or subsidies and a closed “play to earn” ecosystem.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="how-to-invest-in-scaling-ecosystem">How to Invest in Scaling Ecosystem&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Blockchain is the Internet of Value, while the traditional Internet is the Internet of Information; Information data is transmitted by bandwidth, while value exchange is undertaken by liquidity. The first thing that the public chain ecosystem needs to achieve is the flow of value, followed by the efficient exchange of value. Then, based on the efficient exchange of value, productivity increased by establishing applications that meet the needs of users, and finally a blockchain world created featured in efficiency, permissionlessness and censorship resistance, endowed with democratic and anti-vice mechanisms that are open inclusive and transparent.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thanks to smart contracts, the blockchain application is not only limited to being a decentralized ledger but also generates new things such as Non-fungible Token for ownership definition in the digital world and DAO, a new governance organization structure with homogeneous tokens as the cornerstone of governance. These innovations, combined with existing Internet applications, have given rise to more application scenarios, but the current blockchain infrastructure is not well equipped to support the implementation of these application scenarios.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First is the issue of scaling. Both TPS and data availability need scaling. This has been explored by ZK Rollup and Validium and their work has been productive. In addition, there are other Layer 2/Layer 1 solutions such as Optimistic Rollup, Plasma, Solana and Celestia. Scaling technology itself is the best investment target. At this stage, we can put more attention to the on-chain storage technology. After scaling, high TPS and reliable data availability can greatly improve the performance of the blockchain, which allows more complex applications to be built on the blockchain. These applications can be divided into two categories: Internet product blockchainlized and Blockchain original innovation.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Internet product blockchainlized: The most obvious examples are the applications in the GameFi field, such as GameFi on-chain real-time matchmaking settlements, on-chain real-time communication and large-scale payments.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Blockchain original innovation: High-performance blockchain infrastructure allows more frequent and intensive value exchange behavior than before, which will greatly promote the cost-efficiency of value flow. Innovative applications should be those that can truly improve the efficiency of capital utilization and thus achieve higher productivity. Moreover, high-performance blockchains make it possible to achieve &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/%E6%95%B0%E6%8D%AE%E8%B5%84%E6%9C%AC%E6%97%B6%E4%BB%A3-%E6%89%98%E9%A9%AC%E6%96%AF%C2%B7%E6%8B%89%E5%A7%86%E4%BB%80-Thomas-%E7%BB%B4%E5%85%8B%E6%89%98%C2%B7%E8%BF%88%E5%B0%94-%E8%88%8D%E6%81%A9%E4%BC%AF%E6%A0%BC-Mayer-Sch%C3%B6nberger/dp/B07KLFLYH9">data capital market&lt;/a> liquidity, which is a groundbreaking innovation that allows data, as a factor of production in the information age, to flow and be applied fully, with reasonable and fair benefit distribution.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Next is the issue of liquidity, which is divided into horizontal and vertical liquidity here.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Horizontal liquidity refers to the transfer of value among different public chains/L2 ecosystems. When a new public chain/L2 ecosystem is formed, users need a good value exchange tool, sometimes called a bridge, to migrate from the original ecosystem. Currently, traditional bridge tools have some security issues, which may lead to the loss of users' money and sometimes even trigger chain effects. The good news is that there are new bridge technologies, such as Layerzero, and it is believed that there will be more and better technologies, such as zk bridges which are expected to &lt;a href="https://hackmd.io/@kalmanlajko/rkgg9GLG5">solve many problems&lt;/a> about bridges currently exist. Bridges, as a liquidity portal of ecosystem’s value, can generate more DeFi applications thus capturing more value.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/pseudotheos/status/1511342937262759939">https://twitter.com/pseudotheos/status/1511342937262759939&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Vertical liquidity refers to the transfer of value within the same L1/L2 ecosystem. The optimization of vertical liquidity contributes more to the efficient flow of value, thanks to various innovative DeFi applications including AMM, Yield Farm and Lending. Efficient applications result in less value loss in the exchange process and the value captured in this segment is undoubtedly huge. However, the current solutions are not good enough, as most of them provide liquidity by locking it, which is not an efficient way to use funds. Novel solutions in this area include Tokemak and dAMM, and we can look out for more L2 applications in this area.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The third is the issue of data privacy. No company wants to make all its financial data public so that the whole network can audit its every financial flow. The blockchain on-chain data is in the HTTP era of the Internet, where all information is “transmitted” in clear text, while the emergence of ZK technology can make the blockchain embrace the HTTPS era. It can be believed that almost every transaction on the blockchain in the future can be protected by zero-knowledge technology. At that time, blockchain technology will be able to penetrate every corner of society and protect privacy of transactions while ensuring trustlessness, tamper-proof, openness, security and transparency. The best way to guarantee privacy is in the form of a protocol, serving as a plug-in, which can be built together with other protocols like Lego blocks, and it can be configured, owned and censorship-resistant. In the foreseeable future, the privacy protocol will be mandatory for every application.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Lastly, the wallet plays a crucial role as the gateway to the blockchain world. If compared with the Internet, wallet is like the browser in the Internet era. Information interacts with people through the browser, but value interacts with people through the wallet. It is said that we have entered the Netscape era of blockchain, and MetaMask may be the Netscape that flourished back then, although their endings may be different. However, I think the wallet is far from being good at this moment. One of the most important points is that value does not flow efficiently between different wallets. There may be some compatibility issues that affect interoperability here, but undoubtedly, we need a universal set of standards to define this value interface.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The mentioned above is the infrastructure, the area where value is created and begins to be captured. Only after these issues are improved (which may not be exhaustive) will blockchain technology be able to take off and the Internet of Value be able to connect everyone.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Inside the previous public chain ecosystem, the value was mainly captured by protocols, firstly in the public chain itself, and then in the DeFi field, especially in exchanges and exchange platforms. Here we can refer to the famous &lt;a href="https://www.usv.com/writing/2016/08/fat-protocols/">Fat Protocol Theory&lt;/a>, which has always been &lt;a href="https://messari.io/article/analyst-notes-cracks-in-the-fat-protocol-theory">debatable&lt;/a>. For the moment, however, Fat Protocol Theory is generally correct. In my opinion, this is because the blockchain infrastructure era is still far from over.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Infrastructure construction is long, difficult and labor- and material-intensive, but it is the area with the most notable moat effect. On top of the infrastructure, applications that can bring great benefits are called kinetic applications, and those that create the most value effects must be kinetic applications. To be the infrastructure or the kinetic application is not unchanging, for example, Taobao, once the kinetic application of the Internet, but now serves as a platform that is gradually becoming the infrastructure of Ant Group. The core purpose of infrastructure is to pave the way for kinetic applications and reduce the adoption cost of kinetic applications.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The kinetic age of blockchain has not yet arrived, and as it does, there is no doubt that the Fat Protocol Theory will fail (although some problems have already emerged). At this moment, it would be wise to bet on the infrastructure track that can reduce the cost of application adoption. The adoption cost includes not only economic costs, but also efficiency, technology thresholds, and even belief costs (reflected in blockchain fundamentalism such as decentralization, trustlessness, and censorship resistance).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With the gradual application of ZK Rollup in the L2 era and even &lt;a href="https://medium.com/starkware/fractal-scaling-from-l2-to-l3-7fe238ecfb4f">the arrival of the era of L3 and L4&lt;/a>, the kinetic era of blockchain will surely become predictable. So who is the leading role in the kinetic era? It must come from areas that could emerge killer applications. These areas include games, entertainment, social networks and virtual reality. Early betting in these areas is also a desirable investment. However, given the difficulty and return ratio, it is not very cost-effective at this stage. When investing in these areas, you can fully consider whether they make full use of the new infrastructure or retain full scalability for the new infrastructure, which enables fast enough,high-value cost control and efficiency improvements. It will greatly improve their competitiveness in the rapidly evolving blockchain infrastructure era.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="references">References&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://zeroknowledge.fm/zero-knowledge-cryptography-the-next-digital-revolution/">Zero Knowledge Cryptography &amp;amp; the Next Digital Revolution - ZK Podcast&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://ethereum-magicians.org/t/a-rollup-centric-ethereum-roadmap/4698">A rollup-centric ethereum roadmap&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://w3hitchhiker.mirror.xyz/7dwD76ZZIlR7ep731K6y9vTTuXGHOojxWSnkXKzqPzI">一文了解Layer2的四大解决方案交易成本对比&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://hackmd.io/@yezhang/S1_KMMbGt">zkEVM - HackMD&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://mirror.xyz/0x3D5FE39342e661776bb5273521F52E99B624288c/NFOsWYCb2eVk612VSnrrCsoKcwI_EMObp_q9uNKa4uA">Ethereum's Ultimate Scaling Explanation and Directory&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://news.ethereum.cn/Layer2/zksync-vs-starkware">zk-rollup 争夺战：zkSync vs. StarkWare&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.geekmeta.com/article/3421070.html">吊打 Optimistic Rollups？StarkWare 的 L2 赛道大揭秘 | Unitimes AMAes AMA&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://mp.weixin.qq.com/s/r7cNMWYPP-9sqjLcKz64Aw">StarkNet 中文开发者 Meetup（文字版）&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://future.a16z.com/how-composability-unlocks-crypto-and-everything-else/">Composability is Innovation&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.panewslab.com/zh/articledetails/D56636383.html">探索以太坊扩容之路：哪个方案才是未来？-PANews&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://future.a16z.com/go-to-market-in-web3">Go-to-Market in Web3: New Mindsets, Tactics, Metrics&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://future.a16z.com/go-to-market-in-web3">Go-to-Market in Web3: New Mindsets, Tactics, Metrics&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://future.a16z.com/community-%E2%89%A0-marketing-why-we-need-go-to-community-not-just-go-to-market/">Community ≠ Marketing: Why We Need Go-to-Community, Not Just Go-to-Market&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://medium.com/starkware/starknet-alpha-2-4aa116f0ecfc">StarkNet Alpha 2&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://mirror.xyz/kuiqian.eth/FW6gE79ksYDgfrDOhW9zse-bGhLBzaMizIlid3iKZ8Q">以太坊扩容方案的明珠&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://medium.com/starkware/hello-cairo-3cb43b13b209">Hello, Cairo!&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://multicoin.capital/2022/03/15/move-move-move/?mc_cid=43fd88cdd6&amp;amp;mc_eid=0b68dd5aad">Multicoin Capital: Move Move Move&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://newsletter.banklesshq.com/p/rollup-tokens-are-coming?s=r">Layer 2 Tokens Are Coming&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://newsletter.banklesshq.com/p/liquidity-is-bandwidth">Liquidity is bandwidth&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.usv.com/writing/2016/08/fat-protocols/">Fat Protocols | Union Square Ventures&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://messari.io/article/analyst-notes-cracks-in-the-fat-protocol-theory">Analyst Notes: Cracks in the Fat Protocol Theory&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://medium.com/starkware/fractal-scaling-from-l2-to-l3-7fe238ecfb4f">Fractal Scaling: From L2 to L3&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://hackmd.io/@kalmanlajko/rkgg9GLG5">Geometry presents: Slush, a proposal for Fractal scaling - HackMD&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="worth-reading">Worth Reading&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://wrongalot.substack.com/p/unfollow-the-money?token=eyJ1c2VyX2lkIjo2NTk5MTM0MCwicG9zdF9pZCI6NTAzNjg3NjYsIl8iOiI3VnR1NSIsImlhdCI6MTY0NzM1Njc5MiwiZXhwIjoxNjQ3MzYwMzkyLCJpc3MiOiJwdWItMjU5MTUiLCJzdWIiOiJwb3N0LXJlYWN0aW9uIn0.lYPfVwsDOu7GtYm4WMA6wlK0XyPGAGXaqlFDkjDGLCg&amp;amp;s=r">Uhttps://www.bubais.top/en/tech/nft-a-revolution/nfollow The Money&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://mirror.xyz/0x3D5FE39342e661776bb5273521F52E99B624288c/I_zTz72C8lZtteRYBxco9p2iPUE77a6rwtgRWeP9e-s">A Look Under the Hood Into Ethereum Technology and Scaling Solut...&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://zeroknowledge.fm/what-is-zexe-part-i/">What is ZEXE? (Part I) - ZK Podcast&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://zeroknowledge.fm/what-is-zexe-part-ii/">What is ZEXE? (Part II) - ZK Podcast&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://zeroknowledge.fm/what-is-zexe-part-iii/">What is ZEXE? (PART III) - ZK Podcast&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://medium.com/blockchain-capital-blog/wtf-is-data-availability-80c2c95ded0f">WTF is Data Availability?&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://barnabe.substack.com/p/understanding-rollup-economics-from?utm_source=url#footnote-anchor-1">Understanding rollup economics from first principles&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.preethikasireddy.com/post/a-normies-guide-to-rollups">A normie's guide to rollups&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://dcbuilder.mirror.xyz/QX_ELJBQBm1Iq45ktPsz8pWLZN1C52DmEtH09boZuo0">The ultimate guide to L2s on Ethereum&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://newsletter.banklesshq.com/p/the-best-ways-to-invest-in-layer?s=r">The best ways to invest in Layer 2&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://medium.com/1kxnetwork/blockchain-bridges-5db6afac44f8">Blockchain Bridges&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://mp.weixin.qq.com/s?__biz=MzU4MTQwMzMxOA==&amp;amp;mid=2247488686&amp;amp;idx=1&amp;amp;sn=a02c7db30f3dddb87ce1a1376b612d9c&amp;amp;chksm=fd494377ca3eca6189517e9c3cf739c2b352417928dccf066dc5cf748614dda77081eb97b89a&amp;amp;scene=21#wechat_redirect">详解10大Layer1与4大Layer2年度进展与竞争格局 |链捕手&lt;/a>&lt;/p></content></entry><entry><title type="text">NFTs: a revolution in digital ownership</title><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://bubais.top/en/tech/nft-a-revolution/"/><id>https://bubais.top/en/tech/nft-a-revolution/</id><updated>2023-04-24T15:10:21+08:00</updated><published>2021-12-14T21:51:33+08:00</published><author><name>不白</name><uri>https://bubais.top/</uri><email>nowhitestar@gmail.com</email></author><rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">This article believes that the core of NFT is the declaration of digital ownership, and the current outbreak of NFT application scenarios is a revolution of digital ownership, and its end may be something called the metaverse. But this article will not write too much on this.</summary><content type="html">&lt;p>This article believes that the core of NFT is the declaration of digital ownership, and the current outbreak of NFT application scenarios is a revolution of digital ownership, and its end may be something called the metaverse. But this article will not write too much on this. This article tries to use simple and straightforward words to clarify what NFT is, what it is useful for, what are the applications in the industry now, what problems exist, and try to explain the future development of NFT. direction to make some judgments.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="what-is-nft">What is NFT&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="1-definition">1. Definition&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>NFT (Non-Fungible Token, Non-Fungible Token) is an encrypted digital proof of rights and interests that cannot be copied or tampered with, and is defined and &amp;quot;minted&amp;quot; by smart contracts. It is a physical collectible. and &amp;quot;digital fingerprints&amp;quot; of virtual assets such as images, music, game props, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Homogenization can be simply understood with the following diagram, that is, homogenized things can be replaced with each other, and their core values ​​are &amp;quot;homogeneous&amp;quot;, while non-homogenization means that the core value is &amp;quot;non-homogeneous&amp;quot;, such as when I was a child. The Water Margin cards are non-homogeneous, and 108 Songjiang cards cannot be exchanged for prizes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://tva1.sinaimg.cn/large/e6c9d24egy1h2bjwo7m86j21gn0u0tbu.jpg" alt="Untitled" title="Source: [What Are NFTs and How Can They Be Used in Decentralized Finance? DEFI Explained](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Xdkkux6OxfM)">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="2-characteristics-and-principles">2. Characteristics and principles&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>NFTs represent verifiable scarcity, portability, and programmability of digital property. NFTs have these properties due to a piece of code (smart contract) residing on a blockchain such as Ethereum that specifies multiple functions that can be used to create new tokens and interact with them.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Verifiable scarcity means that certain NFTs are verifiably limited. This feature comes from the fact that there may be a function called &amp;quot;mint&amp;quot; in the smart contract, which can be called by anyone in the world. When called, this function will check some variables for global count to ensure that it is on the blockchain. Minting of the same type of product (such as the cards representing Messi in the blockchain game Sorare) is less than a certain value (such as 1,000).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Portability refers to the interoperability and tradability of NFTs.
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Interoperability i.e. NFT standards allow NFTs to be transferred across multiple ecosystems, as open NFT standards provide a clear, consistent, reliable and authorized API for reading and writing data.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Tradability means that NFTs can be freely traded and exchanged. Thanks to its non-copyable and tamper-resistant encrypted digital proof of stake properties, blockchains such as Ethereum will become a &amp;quot;machine&amp;quot; that records states, permanently tracking all changes and activities over time, and globalizing these states. Shared, anyone can view it anytime. Everyone in the world can transact with anyone else and do almost anything, including creating, selling, and transferring NFTs.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Programmability means that NFTs can be designed to be dynamic, interactive works that change according to certain conditions. Such as &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://medium.com/ethernitychain/dak-prescott-x-ethernity-89e558ebd880">Dak Prescott&lt;/a>&lt;/em> is such an NFT work, the NFT will change its style every week according to the player's performance: when the QBR score is A standard performance of 60-75, you'll see Dak in futuristic blue and silver attire, maintaining a throwing motion as if ready to lead his team to victory; and a sizzling performance with a QBR rating of 75, Dak would be wearing a fiery red outfit and held high by his teammates.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The following is a comprehensive scenario of NFTs, which fully reflects the various characteristics of NFTs:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;em>I log into a VR casino with my virtual identity (verifiable scarcity), then pull up to a chair and the dealer will recognize my avatar as a TBI (digital representation of property). Since this is my 10th time at the casino and I've been using the heater, my player card is glowing hot (programmable), signaling that other players should come to my table. Casinos like this and decided to send me a virtual &amp;quot;drink ticket&amp;quot; that can be redeemed in any app that recognizes these NFTs like Uber, Eats, Drizzly (portability). - &amp;quot;Crypto Theses for 2022&amp;quot; from Messari&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>A simple operation logic diagram of NFTs is shown in the following figure,&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://tva1.sinaimg.cn/large/e6c9d24egy1h2bjx3bzdtj223b0u0qcl.jpg" alt="NFT逻辑原理.png">&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Suppose Alice owns 888 ETH in the current state and calls the mint function of the RandomCat NFT smart contract, passing it 69 ETH as payment to create RandomCat #420. The Ethereum blockchain will record a new state after this transaction that Alice now has only 819 ETH but has an NFT token in her wallet address representing RandomCat #420 and the RandomCat NFT smart contract address will now be 69 ETH or more.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Now suppose Alice decides to sell her RandomCat NFT to Bob for 100 ETH. As a result of this transaction, the Ethereum blockchain state machine is now again transitioning to a new state, and now the recorded fact is that Alice has 919 ETH and no RandomCat NFT, and Bob now has 100 less ETH but one more RandomCat # 420 NFTs.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>It can be easily seen that smart contracts are the center of the operation of NFTs. There are many NFT smart contracts. At present, the mainstream smart contract protocols include ERC-721, ERC-1155 and ERC-998, etc., which are similar to homogeneous tokens. The differences between the protocol ERC-20 are as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Features/Classes&lt;/th>
&lt;th>ERC-20&lt;/th>
&lt;th>ERC-721&lt;/th>
&lt;th>ERC-1155&lt;/th>
&lt;th>ERC-998&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Definition&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Homogeneous Token&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Non-Fungible Token&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Semi-Fungible Token&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Combinable Non-Fungible Token&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Features&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Tokens are compatible with Ethereum wallets, standardized, universal, compatible, and easy to interact&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Each token is unique and can represent asset ownership&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Can integrate different tokens for packaging&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Can contain multiple ERC-721 and ERC- 20 Tokens&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Divisibility&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Token Divisible&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Token Indivisible&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Conversion Allowed&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Token Indivisible&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Transferability&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Supports transfer between Ethereum smart contracts and decentralized applications&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Supports the transfer of one token at a time&lt;/td>
&lt;td>It can be merged into a token package and transferred in batches, and the token package has an independent ID&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Can be transferred in batches&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Advantages&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Functions such as transfer, request, approval, etc. can be easily realized&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Allows tracking of ownership records of assets, all assets are unique&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Cross-chain, destroyable to improve overall scarcity&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Detachable, synthesizable&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Defects&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Accepting instructions is prone to problems and can easily lead to asset loss&lt;/td>
&lt;td>A contract can only issue one NFT asset&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Information loss; sacrificing the degree of network decentralization&lt;/td>
&lt;td>New standard, to be tested&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Application scenarios&lt;/td>
&lt;td>OMG, SNC, TRX and other tokens&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Collectibles/arts, securities, etc.&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Collectibles, games, virtual worlds, etc.&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Collectibles, games, real estate, etc.&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Representative Projects&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>NFT Worlds, BAYC, CryptoKitties, Hashmasks&lt;/td>
&lt;td>OpenSea Shared Storefront, Rarible&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Aavegotchi&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Source：Organized from Tianfeng Securities, PANews&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It can be seen that, from left to right, after the homogenized token has developed into a non-homogeneous token, the emergence of more new protocols has brought new capabilities and gameplay to NFTs, which also makes NFTs more than just rights and interests. prove. It is an entirely new existence, a very broad extension based on the concept of ownership.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="what-are-nfts-for">What are NFTs for?&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The NFT characteristics brought by the smart contract agreement determine the value and role of NFTs. There is no doubt that with the development of smart contracts, NFTs will have more and more ways to play, and their functions will become more and more powerful, but no matter how it changes, its core is always the concept of ownership. Digital assets and even the data itself can tell the world through NFT technology who a digital asset &amp;quot;belongs&amp;quot; to, but due to the lack of current digital property legislation, it may be more appropriate to describe it as &amp;quot;all tokens&amp;quot;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Around the concept of all tokens, the extended role and value of NFTs, I summarize it into the following aspects.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="1-ownership-tokens-themselves">1. Ownership tokens themselves&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The most direct application scenario is to apply NFTs to the proof of ownership of property itself. Thanks to blockchain technology, this proof of ownership has the natural advantages of being immutable, unforgeable and unreproducible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It can be applied to,&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Proof of ownership of physical property, such as real-world real estate, tickets, and bus tickets, etc., use cases include Mintbase, DigiTix, etc.;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Proof of ownership of virtual property, such as domain names and data assets, use cases include Ethereum Name Service, Unstoppable Domains, Ethereum Name Service (ENS), Ocean Protocol, etc. It is worth mentioning that the proof of ownership of data assets is an innovative application with a huge market and promising potential;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Proof of ownership of intellectual property, which in turn can be divided into,
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Proof of personal time/skills, imagine the scenario of driving license, graduation certificate, internship experience, work experience on the chain in the future, personal background check will not need to exist, use cases include The Microsponsors Marketplace, etc.;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Proof of intellectual property, piracy, infringement and plagiarism are major challenges facing the media and entertainment industry. NFTs can use blockchain technology to prevent fraud and prevent plagiarism of ideas and creative works. Use cases include Blockchain App Factory, etc.;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Decentralized identity. In today's Web 2.0, users can upload ID cards, passports, and work certificates to a designated centralized authority platform to digitize their identities. Users need to manage their identities on different platforms. Relying on NFT technology, users' identities can be decentralized and used on different platforms; at this stage, people's on-chain identities are basically wallet addresses, but the amount of information and application scenarios recorded by wallet addresses are far from enough. Moreover, the wallet addresses on different chains cannot be aggregated to form identity data, and the user's &amp;quot;identity information&amp;quot; cannot be fully presented at present, which requires the maturity of cross-chain technology.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="2-ownership-tokens--defi">2. Ownership tokens + DeFi&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There are countless financial scenarios derived from ownership, and almost all scenarios in the real world can be NFTized. Projects from DeFi to NFTs have begun to show great development potential. One of the typical applications is lending.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Lending, this form is very likely to become the next explosion in the field of decentralized finance. If the market allows users to lease their NFT assets as loan collateral, allowing other users to use other people's NFTs on their own platforms, this will unlock the endless potential of NFTs, which will not only further clarify the valuation of NFTs, It also provides more liquidity. Several platforms have emerged today that can lend NFTs as NFT collateral, such as Starter, UniLend, Lendroid and NFTfi. NFTs owners can borrow through NFTs to make the best use of their idle NFTs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>NFTs can also be used in more complex financial products such as insurance, bonds or options:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Yinsure of Yearn Finance is an example of applying NFTs in the insurance field. In Yinsure, each insurance contract is represented by NFT and can be traded on secondary markets such as Rarible;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The 88MPH project introduces NFT elements to explore the different integration methods of art, NFT and fixed income;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>ERC-20 zero-coupon bonds use a hybrid approach of NFTs and encapsulated ERC-20s for improved liquidity and composability;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>NFT index fund project NFTX has launched a MASK fund for Hashmasks.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="3-ownership-tokens--p2e-play-to-earn">3. Ownership Tokens + P2E (Play to Earn)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The earliest landing attempt of NFT was in games. NFTs based on blockchain technology can record the status and achievements of players in the game, and save the list of items obtained in the game. NFTs can ensure immutable and seamless transfer of records, guaranteeing ownership verification and authenticity of game items. At the same time, game items can also be designed to be used across games, or have a certain exchange value. The problem with traditional games is that these items are not allowed to be transferred, and few games allow the trade or sale of collected items, let alone use across games. NFTs provide a solution to this problem. Allows in-game assets to be transferred to other games. At present, there are two main types of blockchain game play, namely GameFi with centralized characteristics and decentralized Meta game.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>GameFi&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>This mode is one of the most popular and popular scenarios for NFT application projects, with use cases including Axie Infinity, Alien Worlds, NBA Top Shot, Sorare, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In mid-2021, the sales of NFT game Axie Infinity skyrocketed. According to CryptoSlam data, as of December 9, the cumulative transaction volume of NFT game project Axie Infinity exceeded 3.6 billion US dollars, ranking first in the NFT market in terms of transaction volume. The rapid rise of Axie Infinity has driven the rapid development of the entire NFT market sector.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol start="2">
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Meta game&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The representative of the metagame is undoubtedly the decentralized Loot. Its founder is Dom Hofmann. Loot has the following four characteristics: 1. Directly receive coins in smart contracts; 2. Bottom-up community Drive mode; 3. Novel shape and simple design; 4. Large space for subsequent imagination. The most important significance of Loot is that it provides an example of decentralized NFT, adopts a community-driven bottom-up model, and transfers the creation rights of NFT from the project side to the community, which truly stimulates the great creativity of the community.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another great example is Rarity, which was created on Fantom by its founder, Andre Kroger (AC). Strictly speaking, Rarity can be seen as an imitation of Loot. Loot has 8 equipments, Rarity has 11 adventure characters, and the subsequent gameplay is decided by the developer. We see the role of Rarity as a kind of game atom, where members of the community write games together.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rarity differs from Loot in the following ways:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Rarity is based on Fantom instead of Ethereum;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Rarity casting without restrictions;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Rarity is more centralized under AC.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>As of October 14, more than 4 million characters have been minted by more than 170,000 holders. Developed a variety of visual UI interfaces, trading markets, adventure upgrades, adventure maps, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="4-ownership-tokens--c2e-create-to-earn">4. Ownership Tokens + C2E (Create to Earn)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Advances in AI will transform Play-to-earn into Create-to-earn. The Create-to-earn model, which brings new services to players through virtual creation, is mainly achieved through creators providing value-added services to players. Creators gain real-world benefits by being able to create virtual reality. Under the economic incentives, the creation of users is stimulated, which is dominated by player creation, bringing immersive experience and social scenes, and has seen the prototype of the metaverse.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This mode mainly includes:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>ART&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>NFTs allow artists to own the copyright of their own artworks, and buyers can ensure the authenticity and authority of the artworks they buy, preventing piracy and counterfeiting. Blockchain can solve the proof of ownership problem. Artists no longer have to rely on third parties for protection of their works, eliminating the medium of middlemen and ensuring more income for artists. The tokenization of digital art makes it easier to create, trade, and earn royalties from NFTs. Due to the catalysis of the epidemic and other reasons, this form has become one of the scenarios with the most NFT application projects, and its subdivision forms include star cards/digital art, avatar OG, generative art, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Among the top 5 projects by transaction volume in the NFT market, 2 to 4 are art projects, namely CryptoPunks, Art Blocks, and Bored Ape Yacht Club. Major platforms include OpenSea, MakersPlace, SuperRare, KnownOrigin, Mintbase, Nifty Gateway, Rarible;&lt;/p>
&lt;ol start="2">
&lt;li>&lt;strong>MUSIC&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The NFT marketplace promises to open up a world of virtual collectibles to music fans. In the K-pop realm, many fans have embraced the NFT collectible format—independently released albums are highly sought after. Musicians can create digital goods to sell, and they can decide how many versions are made available in perpetuity before the work is released to the market. Not only can NFT platforms bring sales to musicians, they can also bring in better revenue than music platforms such as Spotify and iTunes. Use cases include Rocki, Rarible, Mintbase, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol start="3">
&lt;li>&lt;strong>FASHION&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>NFTs related to the fashion industry can also be put into use on the Ethereum blockchain network, launching projects. More and more tools and technologies will be rolled out to allow designers and developers to collaborate on virtual clothing materials, shapes, and interoperable game and VR fashion assets. Startup Digitalax, for example, launched the world’s first NFT protocol for the digital fashion industry — and it’s confident it can bring these cutting-edge digital assets into the mainstream. Digitalax is the first dedicated purely digital fashion auction trading platform and open source digital fashion toolkit.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol start="4">
&lt;li>&lt;strong>KNOWLEDGE&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The current content production and distribution model based on the Web2.0 model fails to effectively protect the interests of creators. There are two economic benefits to decentralizing creators:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>transfer content ownership from traditional internet platforms to creators;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Create a revenue stream for long-tail creators.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Like Mirror, it is a decentralized content distribution platform where creators raise money from fans by issuing tokens. After their works are minted into NFTs, the income from article reprints and rewards will be shared with fans according to their contributions, and creators need to open columns through WRITE tokens.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In addition, in the academic world, several centralized publishing institutions in the Web2.0 era monopolized the copyright of academic papers, and even the publishers of academic papers even need to pay for downloading their own papers after the papers are published. In the era of Web3.0, scholars can publish their papers on the blockchain. Combined with NFT to protect their copyrights and intellectual property rights, people anywhere in the world can access their academic achievements for free, which not only reduces the barriers to academic exchanges , it can also promote academic equity, and academic institutions in many poor countries are now struggling to pay for expensive paper downloads.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="5-ownership-token--ip--fan-economy">5. Ownership Token + IP / Fan Economy&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Whether in P2E or C2E mode, NFTs are inseparable from the community. In both cases, people gather for play or creation. In addition to this, there is another force that attracts people to form active communities, and that is IP.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The value of NFTs has strong content and media attributes. One of the very important dimensions is the audience's acceptance of the NFT. This is exactly the same as the popular IP in the traditional entertainment field. Whether the IP is popular also depends on whether it can obtain large-scale group identity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Through fans' recognition of idols (IP), idols are given value and accumulated, so as to further shape a business model that can generate economic benefits and form a fan economy. The NBA Top Shot, which recently set a transaction record of 400 million US dollars, is such a strong IP-based NFTs that makes full use of the business logic of the fan economy. In addition, use cases in this regard include Sorare, which focuses on football IP, and Starly, which is doing Instagram for Web 3.0.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The above are the five role scenarios of NFTs. Of course, these application scenarios of NFTs do not exist in isolation. For example, the concept of all tokens C2E and the concept of ownership IP will be integrated to a large extent. For example, in the application in the music field, musicians It is the IP itself. Many people are fans of certain musicians. In addition to purchasing digital album collections created by musicians, it is easy to spontaneously form a fan economy. And the NBA Top Shot and Sorare in the P2E mode of all tokens are also based on the huge fan effect of basketball and football.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="nft-industry-market">NFT Industry Market&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="1-investment-trends">1. Investment Trends&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>2021 is known as the &amp;quot;first year&amp;quot; of NFT. Artists, celebrities, and giant companies have entered the NFT market one after another. The record-high NFT price has made it the focus of public attention.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>According to incomplete statistics, from January 1, 2021 to December 10, 2021, 325 financing events occurred in the global NFT-related industry, of which 267 disclosed the specific financing amount, and the total financing amounted to 6.5 billion US dollars.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>![Untitled](![](./_image/2022-05-17/Untitled 1.png))&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Specifically, the entire market is in its infancy, with strategic investment, seed/angel accounting for 26.46% and 34.77%, and there are still plenty of opportunities to participate in early investment in good projects.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.notion.so/66f7d6cdc07241c180b02037150324d6">NFT 融资轮次&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The million-dollar financing was outstanding, accounting for 54.77%, followed by the tens of millions of dollars and 100 million dollars. This is because most project financing is in the early stage and the amount involved is not large.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.notion.so/dc233522b8ec43b5a70b207d1a70b04f">融资金额&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From the perspective of subdivision scenarios, the P2E model occupies the majority, accounting for 32.31%, followed by financial applications and NFT transactions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.notion.so/1177a7bb3a904b05aa7867f0a34a9620">NFT 产业赛道&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Among them, Sorare, a digital football NFT collection platform, ranks among the top with two financing amounts of 680 million and 532 million US dollars. Forte completed a $725 million financing, and Dapper Labs completed two more than $100 million financing, for a total of $555 million. In addition, Ripple, Sky Mavis, Alchemy, Axie Infinity, Mythical Games, Candy Digital, Merit Circle and Animoca Brands have raised more than 100 million yuan.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Looking at the domestic situation, 10 financing events occurred in China. Among them, Animoca Brands, a Hong Kong mobile game development company, received a financing amount of 139 million US dollars, which is the only financing event in China that ranks among the top ten international financing amounts. In addition, the NFT digital art e-commerce platform TheOne.art and the NFT trading platform 84club also received 10 million and 2 million yuan of investment respectively.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Source: Organized from Zero One Finance, Golden Finance&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="2-industry-structure">2. Industry structure&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The layered logic of the NFT industry value chain is as follows: according to the NFT flow, it is divided into three layers, from bottom to top, the infrastructure layer, the protocol layer and the application layer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://tva1.sinaimg.cn/large/e6c9d24egy1h2bjxz9638j21o20u0n9r.jpg" alt="NFT市场格局图.jpg" title="Source: Collated from A&amp;amp;T Capital, Messari">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The following article will briefly introduce the main representative applications of each level.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="infrastructure-layer">Infrastructure layer&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>It mainly covers the underlying public chain, side chain / Layer2, development tools, token standards, storage and wallets. This layer captures value based on NFT minting, such as the underlying public chain and side chain / Layer 2 captures the Gas Fee generated by minting. The greater the number of NFTs, the greater the value captured by this layer.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Public Chain&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Currently, the NFT space has been dominated by Ethereum, Flow, and the smaller Wax. Most NFT applications will likely need to transition from the Ethereum mainnet to a layer 2 solution or sidechain while relying on Ethereum as a settlement layer. Other base layers (Tier 1), such as Solana, are actively building out their NFT infrastructure, such as Metaplex, which enables individuals to build their own NFT storefronts and publish NFT collections with customizable royalty distributions.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol start="2">
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Side Chain&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Polygon: The biggest advantage so far is its compatibility with Ethereum, which reduces the learning curve for users and developers. Additionally, Polygon has used its tokens to incentivize Bridges to connect to its network very well. Notably, Polygon is doubling down on NFTs for gaming and non-fungible token projects in a new $100 million fund.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Enjin: High profile as an NFT Tier 2 solution, the first platform to offer token injections with a fixed sticky curve per token. Enjin recently raised $18 million for its NFT scaling solution, Efinity, a new blockchain built as a Polkadot parachain.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Immutable: The developers of Gods Unchained, Immutable Labs are about to release their Ethereum layer 2 scaling solution ImmutableX, this layer 2 is built using ZK-Rollups, which the Immutable team claims is more suitable for NFT-based applications.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ronin: A typical example of this is Axie Infinity, which, instead of relying on other third parties, went down the road of building its own sidechain, Ronin, which has so far been effective in reducing gas costs and increasing user adoption .&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;ol start="3">
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Token Standard&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>At present, the most mainstream token standards are ERC-721, ERC-1155 and ERC-998, which have been introduced above.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol start="4">
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Development Tools&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Forte: It will provide developers with a complete set of tools so that developers can integrate blockchain technology and NFTs into game products without breaking existing games (of course, they can also create new ones from 0). games); players do not need complex operations, they can directly manage their own NFTs and conduct transactions through Forte's platform.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Stardust: is a platform designed for game developers to easily build games in the metaverse. Just as PlayFab provides a platform for anyone to build scalable games, Stardust enables game developers to easily create and manage NFTs in their games without requiring any blockchain code. The platform is accessible to everyone from indie developers to AAA studios, and it is currently very time-consuming and expensive for developers to build a fast, secure and scalable game on the blockchain, and Stardust solves this problem.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;ol start="5">
&lt;li>&lt;strong>钱包&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Rainbow: is a fun, easy and secure way to create an Ethereum wallet, collect NFTs and explore the new world of Web3.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>MetaMask: Also known as Little Fox Wallet, is a software cryptocurrency wallet for interacting with the Ethereum blockchain. It allows users to access their Ethereum wallets through browser extensions or mobile apps, which can then be used to interact with decentralized applications.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;ol start="6">
&lt;li>&lt;strong>存储&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>IPFS: InterPlanetary File System (IPFS for short) is a network transfer protocol designed to create persistent and distributed storage and sharing of files. It is a content-addressable peer-to-peer hypermedia distribution protocol. Nodes in the IPFS network will constitute a distributed file system. It is an open source project that has been developed with the help of the open source community since 2014.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>NFT.Storage: is a long-term storage service designed for off-chain NFT data (such as metadata, images, and other assets) up to 31GiB. Data is content addressed using IPFS, which means that a URL pointing to a piece of data (&amp;quot;ipfs://...&amp;quot;) is completely unique to that data. IPFS URLs can be used for NFTs and metadata to ensure that NFTs can always actually reference the expected data (eliminating things like rug pulls).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Pinata: is the first multimedia hub for NFT creators, builders and artists in the Web 3 decentralized world. Since 2018, Pinata's vision has been to create a unique sense of belonging for every creator on the internet. Pinata is the largest pinning service on IPFS, enabling users to upload, manage and share content with anyone, anywhere, anytime.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="protocol-layer">Protocol layer&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>This layer includes the NFT minting protocol (Mint &amp;amp; Launch) and the primary circulation market (Sell &amp;amp; Trade) and some financial applications.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Most of the protocols take into account NFT casting and first-level circulation to further capture value, which is why Mintable introduces the concept of Gasless item to attract users to mint and conduct subsequent transactions on the same platform. Only after the transaction is NFT on the chain to capture the first-level Transaction value, this part can be divided into P2E, C2E and community mode according to the gameplay mode.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The combination of NFT and finance has an extremely wide range of applications. The protocol layer mainly includes liquidity protocols and decentralized finance (DeFi). Liquidity protocols are mainly used for value discovery of NFTs. This type of agreement does not mint NFTs, but price NFTs in various ways. In the future, value capture is likely to be similar to DEXs and oracles, based on providing liquidity and basic financial services. DeFi NFTs, mainly NFTs minted by DeFi activities, unlike other minting protocols, mainly capture value through minting activities.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>P2E (Play to Earn)&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Projects in this mode mainly include sports (which can also be grouped into IP projects) and games/metaverses. Participants can gain profits from the game. The representative projects are as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://nbatopshot.com/">NBA Top Shot&lt;/a> (Sports): A game focusing on NBA NFT card collection jointly launched in cooperation with the NBA League, the content of the cards is mainly the iconic characters of some star players action. NBA fans buy, sell, trade and collect digital signature moves of the season. Features of the game include buying, collecting, trading, and tournament gameplay.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://sorare.com/">Sorare&lt;/a> (Sports): Based on Ethereum, a fantasy football game developed by the startup Sorare. Players can buy and trade club- or league-certified NFT player cards to form their own teams, each with its own level of scarcity and uniqueness, and each player card is rated based on their performance in real-world games. Players can participate in fantasy football matches on the platform and receive card and token rewards after matching the full lineup.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://axieinfinity.com/">Axie Infinity&lt;/a> (game): Axie Infinity is a chain game that collects and raises all kinds of strange creatures. In addition to the ordinary collection attributes, Axie also added unique combat attributes, becoming one of the earliest NFT pets that can fight. The Axie team also launched a customized Ethereum sidechain Ronin for the game in February, which uses POA consensus to increase the verification speed to relieve the pressure of Ethereum network congestion and player gas fees.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://alienworlds.io/">Alien Worlds&lt;/a> (game): DeFi games based on the WAX ​​public chain, players can earn Trilium (TLM) through mining, and there is a certain chance for each mining Mine NFTs. Trilium can be used to pledge to one or more of the six planets in the game, and after signing up as a planetary director candidate, players will have the possibility to rule the planet. NFT game cards introduce innovative gameplay over time, including &amp;quot;shining&amp;quot; to upgrade cards and combat in fighting games.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://decentraland.org/">Decentraland&lt;/a> (Metaverse): A virtual world built on Ethereum, similar to Cryptovoxel, providing land in the form of NFT, avatar outfits, and content servers. In addition, Decentraland utilizes its proprietary cryptocurrency, MANA, to subsidize the operations and programs of the Metaverse, and act as a currency for transactions between users.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.sandbox.game/">The Sandbox&lt;/a> (Metaverse): A pixel sandbox building game similar to Minecraft and Roblox, players can create digital assets in the form of NFTs in The Sandbox VoxEdit Upload it to the store, and create games on your own property with Game Maker's simple drag-and-drop method to attract other players to participate.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;ol start="2">
&lt;li>&lt;strong>C2E (Create to Earn)&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Projects in this mode need to be realized by creators providing value-added services to players, mainly including music, fashion, art/primary market, content and comprehensive types of projects. The representative projects are as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://royal.io/">Royal&lt;/a> (Music): On this platform, users can buy the rights to the songs of their favorite musicians and get royalties through this.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.digitalax.xyz/homepage">Digitalax&lt;/a> (fashion): is the first NFT live marketplace to bring users' unique personality and style into the native digital realm - with a verifiable utility layer , open source material library, sustainable digital physical supply chain and can be used for staking. It's easy to find and collect digital fashion NFTs, all made by outstanding independent designers and brands.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://makersplace.com/">Makersplace&lt;/a> (primary market): Established in 2018, the earliest NFT artwork casting platform has certain thresholds for artworks and artists.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://superrare.co/">SuperRare&lt;/a> (primary market): Rare art minting trading platform.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.larvalabs.com/cryptopunks">CryptoPunks&lt;/a> (art): An NFT built on Ethereum founded in 2017 and the first to inspire the ERC-721 standard. It issues tokens by transforming an ERC-20 contract, generating 10,000 completely different 24x24, 8-bit style pixel art images.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://larvalabs.com/autoglyphs">Autoglyphs&lt;/a> (art): The second NFT project of Larva Labs, the development team of CryptoPunks, is a Generative Art platform.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://mirror.xyz/">Mirror&lt;/a> (content): Mirror's platform token $WRITE (ERC-20) represents the author's right to publish content on the platform, and content creators need to destroy $WRITE in order to To open their own column, the Mirror team chose a group of creators as the platform's first writers and held a weekly $WRITE Race, and put tokens to the authors voted by the community users to allow them to open the column. Crowdfunding is conducted by issuing work tokens to fans. After the work is completed, it will be put on the chain in the form of NFT. The income generated by article reprinting, rewarding, and auction will be divided according to the contribution of fans in crowdfunding.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.darkblock.io/">Darkblock&lt;/a> (content): Darkblock gives creators more control over the distribution of their content, including comics, ebooks, podcasts, music, movies, news, pay-per-view Paid, YouTube, OnlyFans, Patreon, Metaverse Assets, and more. Whether through sales, advertising revenue, or rentals, the goal is to keep revenue flowing to creators by giving them the keys to their content.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://terravirtua.io/">TerraVirtua&lt;/a> (comprehensive): Minting and trading platform for art, collectibles, game IP, etc. The operating environment is highly compatible, enabling users to display, trade, and interact with NFTs in an immersive way; at the same time, its virtual interfaces based on 3D Fancave, Terradome, and Galleries, as well as mobile AR applications, have a good user experience and strong IP resources.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.mintbase.io/zh">Mintbase&lt;/a> (comprehensive): A trading market based on NEAR ecology, users can create and sell NFTs such as music, artwork, tickets, photography, etc.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;ol start="3">
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Community&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>This model is mainly established by creating a community atmosphere, which is different from DAO, which does not necessarily require the formation of an organized autonomous community. This article categorizes it as IP/fan economy and social.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Next World Culture (IP): Next World Culture is a cross-dimensional virtual IP content development operator. It develops content around the pan-entertainment field and cross-circle carriers. It has developed a &amp;quot;live-action animation&amp;quot; web drama &amp;quot;The Hidden Rivers and Lakes&amp;quot;. After 2018, the company officially transformed, developed virtual idol IPs around artists and brands, and produced Di Lieba's avatar &amp;quot;Dilli Lengba&amp;quot; and Huang Zitao's avatar IP &amp;quot;Taosman&amp;quot;; then it turned to expand original Virtual idol IP development, launched the original national style hyper-realistic virtual KOL &amp;quot;Ling&amp;quot; and domestic virtual DJ &amp;quot;Purple&amp;quot;.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.sportzchain.com/">SportZchain&lt;/a> (Fan Economy): A blockchain-powered platform that allows fans to manage their favorite teams, games, leagues, events, and more . Provide direct power to fans not only to follow and interact, but also to actively participate in various decisions of the team. SportZchain provides blockchain-based tools for sports teams and leagues to help them better engage and monetize their audiences.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://chingari.io/">Chingari&lt;/a> (Social): Founded in November 2018, users can download and upload short videos, and purchase items in the app, and its co-founder believes it will become Fastest Growing &amp;quot;Social Token App&amp;quot; in India. Since its redesign in June 2020, Chingari has been trying to fill the vacuum created by TikTok's ban in India. Since then, Chingari's user base is said to have grown exponentially.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://monaconft.io/">Monaco Planet&lt;/a> (social): The next-generation SocailFi platform, as a SocialFi product that focuses on the development concept of &amp;quot;ownership and governance rights are determined by users&amp;quot;, Monaco Planet adopts &amp;quot;content mining The &amp;quot;mine&amp;quot; model allows users to get the native token MONA rewards by following, commenting and liking, as well as NFT display and pledge.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;ol start="4">
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Finance&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Finance at the protocol layer is mainly liquidity protocols and DeFi.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Liquidity protocols are mainly protocols that provide pricing for NFTs. At present, the three solutions are: one is buyer pricing, such as TopBidder pricing through auction; the other is seller pricing, such as NiftEx / NFT20 / NFTX through sellers pledge NFT and generate ERC-20 to provide initial liquidity to generate pricing; third, third-party pricing Pricing, such as Upshot, generates pricing through the predicted behavior of random users. These liquidity protocols are necessary financial infrastructure, providing NFT value discovery for upper-layer complex applications.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.niftex.com/">NiftEx&lt;/a> (Liquidity Protocol): Launched in May 2020, allows staking NFTs and splitting their ownership into ERC-20 to facilitate liquidity, as of July 7 As of today, the market value of all staked NFTs is $4.4M.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://upshot.io/">Upshot&lt;/a> (Liquidity Protocol): Open Beta will be launched in May 2021, using the prediction market to provide price discovery of NFTs, no need to enter exact prices, just complete a series of simple choices question, choose the one you think is more valuable from two random pictures.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://nft20.io/">NFT20&lt;/a> (Liquidity Protocol): Launched in November 2020, allowing NFT to be pledged and generate its ERC-20 token derivatives, which can be traded on dex such as Uniswap to promote liquidity sex. As of July 7, the market value of all staked NFTs is $1.4M.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://nftx.org/">NFTX&lt;/a> (Liquidity Protocol): Launched in January 2021, allows staking NFTs and splitting their ownership into ERC-20, as of July 7, the market value of all staked NFTs for $3.2M.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>DeFi mainly represents protocols that utilize NFTs as asset representation tools, such as Uniswap LP tokens and yinsure policies. Compared with the NFTs minted by the art and collectibles minting protocol, these NFTs are mainly reflected in the different minting methods, which are minted through financial activities.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://uniswap.org/">Uniswap V3&lt;/a> (DeFi): Launched in May 2021, representing LP Token as NFT, defining the liquidity value under different market-making strategies. As of December 11, the total locked volume is $8.29B.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="http://www.aavegotchi.com/">Aavegotchi&lt;/a> (DeFi): Launched in March 2021, obtained by mortgaging the interest-paying deposit certificate aToken on the Aave lending platform, expanding the use of NFT to game scenarios. As of December 11, the total locked volume is $11.15B.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://yinsure.finance/">Yinsure.finance&lt;/a> (DeFi): The unique policy is tokenized with NFT, which can flow in the secondary market, increasing the liquidity of the policy. As of December 11, the total locked volume is $3.93B.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="application-layer">Application layer&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The applications derived from the tokens generated by the protocol layer, such as the NFT traded in the representative project OpenSea in the pan-secondary market, are mainly composed of various minting protocol platforms in the protocol layer. The value capture at this level is mainly based on traffic and demand realization, such as social networking and curation. How to gather traffic and realize is the core value point. This layer mainly includes vertical fields, pan-secondary markets and finance.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Vertical field&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The vertical field mainly refers to NFT data analysis providers/platforms in the data field, which also includes data trading platforms, as well as DAOs and curatorial communities.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A comprehensive data provider has not yet emerged in the NFT data field. Existing data is either not comprehensive enough in NFT coverage or incomplete in data dimension. In addition, there is also a lack of a full-featured NFT search engine, which is an important traffic portal in the future.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://cryptoart.io/">Cryptoart.io&lt;/a> (Data Platform): A data platform focusing on the field of crypto art. Provides information on crypto art, crypto artists, and macro crypto art data analysis.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://nonfungible.com/">Nonfungible&lt;/a> (data platform): Data platform covering Ethereum NFT, including mainstream NFT projects in the market, historical and real-time NFT industry data, and NFT-related industry research.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://oceanprotocol.com/">Ocean&lt;/a> (Data Exchange Platform): Ocean Protocol is a decentralized data exchange protocol designed to unlock data and provide fairer results for data users. Ocean Protocol allows data providers to interact with data consumers through a decentralized data marketplace, while guaranteeing control, auditability, transparency, and compliance for all participants.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The DAO community is driven by intrinsic values ​​(like social status) and extrinsic values ​​(like future development). The job of the curator is to create an ecosystem for these two motives to live in harmony. For ordinary NFT creators, one of the pain points is that their works cannot get initial traffic. We are now seeing curators build deeper relationships with their superfans by bundling premium services. Therefore, curation projects can discover more potential value for users while helping NFT creators to market themselves.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://whale.me/">Whale DAO&lt;/a> (DAO): Curated community, by issuing a community token, issue FT token Whale based on pledged &amp;quot;valuable&amp;quot; NFT, as of July 7th , the Whale asset pool is valued at $4.5m.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://flamingo.finance/">Flamingo&lt;/a> (DAO): Flamingo is a DAO organization focusing on encrypted art investment, its members have the right to jointly decide the NFT artwork to be purchased, and can transfer the NFT purchased by DAO Conduct spinoffs, lending, staking, curation, and more. There are certain threshold requirements to become a Flamingo DAO. You need to donate some ETH as a condition for membership, and the number of members is limited to 100.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.metapurse.fund/">MetaPurse&lt;/a> (curated): MetaPurse is a MetaKoven-funded crypto-community-native venture capital fund focused on investing in crypto art, virtual assets, and funding early-stage projects. Different from other ROI-driven crypto funds, MetaPurse takes promoting NFT ecology as its main goal. It recently showcased its purchased crypto art by curating an NFT VR exhibition.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://collab.land/">Collab.land&lt;/a> (curated): Collab.land is a Telegram Bot-based solution to help crypto startups build early communities. For NFT creators, Collab.land will assist them in curating, and participants at different levels in the creator's community will present exclusive content.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;ol start="2">
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Secondary market&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>This category is mainly the secondary market formed after NFT is minted. Different from the primary market, this type of platform will assume the responsibilities of the secondary market, and most of them include the NFTs produced by the main casting platforms.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://opensea.io/">OpenSea&lt;/a> (pan-secondary market): Launched in December 2017, it is currently the largest NFT trading platform, with sales exceeding 10 billion US dollars in November.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.auctionity.com/">Auctionity&lt;/a> (Pan-Secondary Market): Launched in beta in January 2018, it is an on-chain auction house for crypto collectibles.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://tokentrove.com/">TokenTrove&lt;/a> (pan-secondary market): launched in October 2019. Mainly for the secondary market of games, especially Gods Unchained.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;ol start="3">
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Finance&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Financial projects at the unknown application layer mainly include mortgage lending and asset management tools.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Mortgage lending mainly represents an agreement for NFT as the underlying asset to realize mortgage lending. At present, due to the lack of NFT liquidity and pricing problems, mortgage lending can only be realized in the form of P2P. But referring to the DeFi iteration path, from ETHLend to Aave, P2Pool may be the next upgrade path.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://nftfi.com/">NFTfi&lt;/a> (Lending): Launched in February 2020, in the form of P2P, borrowers put their NFT assets on the market as collateral, and then lenders in the market People come to quote. As of July 7, the loan amount was $4.8m.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://pawnhouse.io/">Pawnhouse&lt;/a> (lending): The beta version will be launched in July 2021, also in the form of P2P, borrowers put their NFT assets on the market as collateral, and then the market Lenders on the list to quote.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Asset management tools are mainly asset management tools in the upper layer of the NFT industry chain, similar to asset management platforms such as Zapper and DeBank in DeFi. There are currently fewer projects.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://nftbank.ai/">NFT Bank&lt;/a> (asset management): Launched in June 2020, an asset management platform for NFTs.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h1 id="problems-with-nfts">Problems with NFTs&lt;/h1>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>The legal protection system is not sound enough&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>As mentioned earlier in this article, the field of NFT is an application form that extends around the concept of ownership, which is the so-called NFT for everything. It is worth mentioning, however, that ownership is a legal concept as old as human civilization. In law, property is &amp;quot;the right to enjoy and dispose of things in the most absolute manner&amp;quot;, and when it comes to your house, it's clear that you bought it - it's your absolute property. There are two types of tangible property (such as house, car, etc.) and intangible property (such as intellectual property).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The law does not specify that mere data or information can be protected by intellectual property rules so that it can be &amp;quot;owned&amp;quot; by someone. In a democratic society, information and data, like ideas, flow freely, and data itself is not something that can be appropriated or &amp;quot;owned.&amp;quot; It is likely that some common law systems are flexible enough to extend the application of property law to certain types of information-only cryptoassets, but reconciling this concept with freedom of speech and information enshrined in international conventions23 seems comparable difficulty.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Without legislative intervention, the absence of information property rights will continue to pose thorny issues for digital asset stakeholders.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another challenge posed by using NFTs to &amp;quot;sell&amp;quot; limited licenses or rights to use certain digital artworks is - how to effectively &amp;quot;attach&amp;quot; contracts/terms and conditions to NFTs so that NFT buyers (and future purchasers) are bound by it.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol start="2">
&lt;li>There is currently no means to prevent counterfeiting&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>There is currently no way to determine who is the real human creator of a piece of art by looking at the data contained in an NFT. The result is an increasing number of cases of NFT forgery, in which scammers create NFTs and present them as the work of a particular well-known artist. A quick Google search on the topic reveals that NFT forgery is a rapidly growing problem. In some cases, scammers take an image/photo of a real work of art created by an artist, convert it into an NFT, then pretend to be the artist and sell the NFT.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol start="3">
&lt;li>Storage is not safe and stable enough&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>NFT creators can choose two ways to store metadata on-chain and off-chain. On-chain storage costs are high and traffic is congested, but metadata will exist permanently with the token. Off-chain storage restrictions are small, but metadata exists in theory. risk of loss. At present, the solutions available for off-chain storage include centralized data storage, IPFS, and decentralized cloud storage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Centralized storage is obviously not a good approach, the original file may be lost or corrupted, but even if the data is stored on IPFS, it is possible that only one node hosts the content and no other nodes back it up, if the storage Its only node is disconnected from the network and data may become unavailable. The Memo project is trying to use the developed MEFS system to make up for this deficiency of IPFS. Also, an NFT may point to a wrong file address. If this is the case, the user cannot prove that he actually owns the NFT. All in all, relying on an external system as the core component of an NFT system is fragile.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol start="4">
&lt;li>The technology is not mature enough to cause security problems&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The technology behind NFTs is only a few years old and still hasn't reached maturity. This has led many to question the security and authenticity of NFTs. This is mainly due to the crackability of smart contracts. The recent frequent incidents of hackers stealing assets have constantly reminded people that the security issues of NFT technology cannot be ignored. In addition, the lack of sufficient technical foundation and economic infrastructure, as well as the scalability of blockchain technology, have affected the mainstream use of NFTs.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="the-future-direction-of-nft">The future direction of NFT&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>NFT is too simple, it just performs a digital confirmation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>NFT is too complicated, and everything can be NFT, which means that it has countless ways to play. This way of playing is to move the real world into the virtual world. This step sounds simple, but there are indeed many difficulties to overcome, and the road is long.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At present, NFT is only a carnival for a few people, and its most popular, most participated and most funded areas are still concentrated on art collections. This is still an economic model that gathers traffic and attention, such as The influence and appeal of a celebrity like Elon Musk is enormous. As Tesla CEO, he has driven and influenced the direction of the digital asset market many times, whether it was Dogecoin before or more recently. PEOPLE. Twitter CEO Jack Dorsey has also cast his eye on NFTs, auctioning off his “first tweet” NFT to charity for $2.9 million.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, if the focus of NFT is still on these people, then NFT may lose its real social influence. There is little real social value in adding $1 million to a celebrity like Elon Musk by selling NFTs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, I firmly believe that NFTs are revolutionary because the essence of NFTs is a revolution in ownership.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;quot;Ownership is undoubtedly the most basic concept in society. All forms determine the character of each society, and its form of existence is also the basis for the division of times such as primitive communist society, slave society, feudal society, capitalist society, and socialist society.&amp;quot; — - &amp;quot;The Birth of &amp;quot;Ownership&amp;quot; Masanobu Kato&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I can't predict what the impact and change that NFT can ultimately achieve in this society, but whatever it is, I think it can be called a revolution.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is essentially a distant and bold speculation about NFTs, so what is the direction of NFTs in the near future?&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;quot;I'm not sure how big the bubble of a single NFT in the market can go, but I know that there is still a lack of reliable and universal NFT infrastructure. NFT trading platforms, developer tools, community-oriented business models, and decentralized identity Management/credit management systems are still in their infancy. These core infrastructures will be one of the hottest areas of investment in 2022.&amp;quot; - &amp;quot;Crypto Theses for 2022&amp;quot; from Messari&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I very much agree with Messari's point of view. At present, the NFT field is full of bubbles and opportunities, and the problem that NFT still has is the opportunity for NFT. In addition to the first point I mentioned in the previous section, it takes time for NFT to gradually attract the attention of the entire real society and establish supervision, the other three points are inseparable from the infrastructure construction of NFT.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First, prevent counterfeiting problems. This can not only start with smart contracts, there are many things that can be done from NFT trading platforms. In addition to this, the investment value of the NFT trading platform also benefits from the &amp;quot;bubble&amp;quot; of NFT. It is foreseeable that the use of NFT as a supporting technology for digital collections in a short period of time is still one of its main value functions. With NFT sweeping the art, music, fashion and content worlds, NFT trading platforms are bound to usher in a wave of positives. These fields all rely on creations. In this process, the trading platform that can solve the problem of counterfeiting will inevitably win the game.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Second, storage issues. Relying on an external system as a core component of an NFT system is vulnerable, even though the Memo project is trying to use the developed MEFS system to make up for the shortcomings of IPFS. The ultimate solution is to store NFTs directly on the blockchain, but there are still many problems due to this storage method, such as high fees, very low confirmation speed, anonymity and privacy issues. If these problems can be solved, the value of NFTs can truly be brought into play, and projects that solve these problems will inevitably be valued.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Again, security issues. Although the core of this problem is the smart contract, a complete contract design that is difficult to be broken by calculation is far from being completed by the human brain alone. If developer tools can focus on this point, it will solve one of the core problems of NFTs, and NFTs that solve security problems will truly symbolize ownership. In addition, with the current explosion of NFT projects, a convenient and available one-stop developer tool that integrates multiple functions will inevitably be sought after, which is also in urgent need.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In addition, not to mention the recent popularity of DAOs, the community-oriented (DAO) business model deserves attention. For centralized identity management/credit management, in &lt;a href="https://messari.io/research/mason-nystrom">Mason Nystrom&lt;/a> &amp;quot;&lt;em>[Curation Tokens: Examining the Types of Crypto Curation](https: //messari.io/article/curation-tokens-examining-types-of-crypto-curation)&lt;/em>&amp;quot;, proposes that NFTs such as NFTs will play an integral role in porting real-world certificates and identities to the new world the role of such a view. I agree with it very much, but I think that this day will not come too soon if the three core issues just now are not resolved. Real-world certificates and identity certificates, as active and important information proof materials for users, are important in fidelity, storage and security. On the issue, there is no room for loss. There may be small-scale and experimental applications in the early stage, but large-scale social applications will take time. This is not only a technical issue, but also involves regulatory compliance. Perhaps the alliance chain is the real landing scenario for this application.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In addition, the recent fire of GameFi. In my opinion, it may not be a good choice to invest in specific game projects. Behind the popularity of Axie Infinity, there are not only the general environmental reasons for the epidemic, but also professional community promoters and the environment of countries with a large number of idle labor such as the Philippines. Just because one game is successful doesn't make all game projects full of confidence. The most attractive point of GameFi is that players can make money. This model has already appeared in legendary games around 2000. For players, it is not so important to sell NFT-based game equipment, even if it can bring another game. . There are many factors that affect whether a blockchain game can really become popular. In addition to the ability to make money, other factors such as playability, community operation, stability and bandwidth are all factors to be considered. However, it is a good choice to jump out of GameFi itself and invest in platforms that support GameFi game projects. They can increase the efficiency of new game projects and improve the innovation ability of game projects. For example, rct AI is a good choice. Additionally, gaming guilds like the Good Games Guild and development tools like Stardust are great investment options.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Finally, I will focus on the contribution of NFTs to the data market, which I think is one of the most promising applications of NFTs, although it has not received enough attention. The NFTization of data assets is one of the most important links in the transformation of the entire society from financial capital into the era of data capital. According to the International Data Corporation, while the amount of &amp;quot;potentially useful&amp;quot; data doubled from 20% to 40% from 2012 to 2020, less than 1% of the world's data is actually used and analyzed. The data analytics market will balloon to nearly $100 billion by the end of next year, with companies and users looking to better monetize their data. In Web3, protocols such as Ocean provide a wrapper for these data packets by encouraging public sharing and secure monetization of data and better price discovery through liquid data markets.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Although data as a means of production is the main competitive advantage of many companies, such as advertising revenue and marketing profits involving FAMGA and domestic BATTMD, there are many stakes, but even so, the revolution brought by NFT to the data market is still inevitable of. It is not difficult to argue this point, as Victor Mayer-Schoenberg, the father of big data, has argued and emphasized in his new book, The Age of Data Capital, that our economy is about to shift from financial capitalism to data capitalism era, and the most critical issue in this era is to protect data markets from excessive concentration, not only at the level of participants, but also in the decision-making process.&lt;/p></content></entry></feed>